<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discoverie of the beasts being an exposition of the XIII chapter of the Revelation of Jesus Christ : wherein all true Christians (yet in Babylon) are admonished to come out, and the anti-Christians fore-told what their plagues will be / by I.W.</title>
            <author>I. W.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 119 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 51 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67263</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W41</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6846</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13091471</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13091471</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97365</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67263)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97365)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 402:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discoverie of the beasts being an exposition of the XIII chapter of the Revelation of Jesus Christ : wherein all true Christians (yet in Babylon) are admonished to come out, and the anti-Christians fore-told what their plagues will be / by I.W.</title>
                  <author>I. W.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>101 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: some text dark and partially illegible.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation XIII --  Criticism, interpretation, etc.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97365:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A DISCO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ERIE OF</hi> THE BEASTS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Being AN EXPOSITION OF THE</hi> XIII. <hi>Chapter</hi> of the <hi>Revelation</hi> of JESUS CHRIST.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherein</hi> All true Chriſtians (yet in <hi>Babylon</hi>) are admoniſhed to come out: And the Anti-chriſtians fore-told what their plagues will be.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> I. W.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Revel. 16. 15.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Behold, I come as a thiefe, bleſſed is he that watcheth and keepeth his garments, leſt he walke naked and they ſee his ſhame.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the year M. DC. XLI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:97365:2"/>
            <head>CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
            <p>AMong the many excellent helps which the Lord at this preſent time hath given unto his Elect, for to diſcover the <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity:</hi> and to direct them in the way which Ieadeth to eternall life, this little <hi>Treatiſe</hi> is a choice and chiefe one. Thou art therefore deſired to peruſe the ſame with an underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and impartiall heart: and ſo doing I doubt not (through Gods bleſſing on they labor) but thou ſhalt reap much comfort and good thereby. I have ſet it forth for the publike good, and do deſire the Father of our <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> that it may prove ſo every where: even a means to raze down <hi>the falſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> and to help forward the buildlng up of Gods Houſe. And ſo prayes he who is thine, if thou be Chriſts,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I C.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:97365:2"/>
            <head>AN <hi>INTERPRETATION OF THE</hi> XIII. <hi>CHAPTER</hi> OF THE <hi>RE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ELATION</hi> OF JESUS CHRIST.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Eternall (whoſe power is over all) from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning hath put enmitie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Serpent and the Woman,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gent.</hi> 3 15.</note> and between the ſeed of the Woman, and the ſeed of the Serpent, whereupon it hath come to paſſe in all ages, that the ſeed of the woman hath laboured to break the Serpents head; that is, to deſtroy his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97365:3"/>works, tread him under foot, and triumph in victory over him: He on the contrarie hath laboured as earneſtly to reſiſt God; to deceive the Nations, and to bring all into condemnation and deſtruction with with himſelf. And amongſt the manifold waies and means, which Satan hath devi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and practiſed, to manifeſt his malice a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and his Saints, none hath been more dangerous, nor more availeable to further iniquity, and cauſe deſtruction; then the Antichriſtian generation, which under the title of the Church and Spouſe of Chriſt, and Miniſters of the Goſpell, have corrupted the earth, and brought the Nations into miſerable bondage and ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie.</p>
            <p>In this 13 Chapter is declared the ſtate, policy, and proceeding of the Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Dominion and Kingdom, as the ſame was ſignified and foreſhewed to <hi>Iohn</hi> the ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt, in a threefold forme,
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, by a Beaſt riſing up out of the Sea, having 7 heads, and 10 hors, <hi>ver.</hi> 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, by a Beaſt comming up out of the earth, having two ho<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>es like
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97365:3"/>the Lamb, but ſpake like the Dragon, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11, 12, 13, 14,</item>
                  <item>Thirdly, by an image of the firſt beaſt, which the ſecond beaſt cauſed them that dwelt on the earth to make, as in <hi>verſ.</hi> 14, 15, 16, 17, 18.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>As the Dominion of the Medes, Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans and Grecians (which perſecuted and deſtroyed the holy people of God, the Iews) were ſignified and foreſhewed to <hi>Daniel</hi> in a viſion, under the formes of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall beaſts, according to the qualities of thoſe Dominions; ſo here the Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an dominion which perſecuted the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and people of Chriſt, was foreſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>Iohn</hi> under the formes of ſuch Beaſts as are here deſcribed, whereby we may learne that as reaſon and judgement is not to be expected in a beaſt, ſo equitie and right is not to be expected in this domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, but the contrarie.</p>
            <p>Concerning the firſt of theſe beaſts, <hi>John</hi> ſayth. <hi>That as I stood upon the ſea ſand. I ſaw a beast riſe up out of the ſea hauing ſeven heads and</hi> 10 <hi>hornes, and upon his hornes</hi> 10. <hi>Crownes: and upon his heads the names of blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy. And the beast which I ſaw was like unto a Leopard, and his feet as the feet of a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97365:4"/>Beare, and his mouth as the mouth of a Lion. and the dragon gaue him his power, and his ſeat, and great authoritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That by this firſt beaſt was ſignified and repreſented ſome ſtate of people and body politique, I preſume no reaſonable man exerciſed in the Scriptures will deny, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (as it hath been ſayd) it is there to be ſeene that ſuch ſtates and dominions as God hath uſed as rods and ſcourges to chaſtiſe and correct his Church and people withall, have been repreſented by beaſts. States and dominions they are of two ſorts, either Eccleſiaſtical or Civil, but of which ſort the State here meant is, there hath been and is great oppoſition. Many underſtand it to be the Romane Empire, to which I cannot conſent, becauſe the Romane Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire is ordeyned of God, and is therefore a lawfull Dominion, But the Dominion here repreſented, is ſayd to be from the dragon that old ſerpent the Deuill, who is ſayd to giue his power and his throne and great au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie unto it, and therefore unlawfull: neither can I conceave it to be any other ciuil dominion for the ſame reaſon. But to be ſhort I vnderſtand it to be an Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall State or Dominion, and in perticular
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97365:4"/>that Dominion which is called the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church repreſentatiue, conſiſting of the Prelacy and Preiſthood of many Nations, as Patriarches, Cardinalls, Archbiſhops, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, with divers other elected perſons, who being called and gathered into Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſells or Synods, (uſually called generall Counſells) did uſurpe and take on them the office of Ieſus Chriſt in making lawes and Canons, erecting Courts, inſtituting of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and officers in matters of Religion, as for the government of the Church and for the worſhip of God) to be of all men obſerved and obeyed. Theſe generall Counſels (or as the Catholicks call it) the Catholicke Church repreſentatiue, haue challenged and exerciſed ſpirituall autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and dominion, According to the text, ouer all kindreds tongus and nations. By their laws and canons they guided and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned them as one uniuerſall or Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke Church, &amp; made them alſo to obſerve their decrees and commaundements for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, this thay haue done both before and alſo ſince the Pope was exalted to his dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, as all hiſtories of the Church do teſtify, So that it hath been and is a great queſtion among the Catholicks whither
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97365:5"/>the authoritie of the Pope, or the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church in caſes of Religion be the greater. And whereas it is ſaid in the 12. verſe that the ſecond beaſt exerciſed all the power of the firſt Beaſt before him, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is confirmed the trueth of this expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. For the ſecond Beaſt being the Pope as hereafter is ſhewed (hath exerciſed the whole power of the Catholick Church or generall counſels, and not of any other ſtate or Dominion.</p>
            <p>Further that this is the firſt beaſt here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented that which followeth (through Gods helpe) ſhall make manifeſt and apparant. But before I doe proceed I deſire the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to obſerve that I do not condemne all vſe of counſells and Synods, but doe hold that divers churches may lawfully be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled together, to conſult and adviſe of matters concerning Religion, and the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, for their inſtruction &amp; infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of their Iudgements, and ſo a good and holy vſe may be thereof. But that any counſells haue ſuch power over the church of Chriſt, as to impoſe vpon them their cômandements for doctrine, and uſurp the goverment of the Churches, and to rule and reigne over them by their lawes and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97365:5"/>and preſcribe rules and formes how God will be worſhipped, as theſe generall counſells haue done, that I doe deny, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contrarie to the perfecton of the holy Scriptures and the practiſe of the Apoſtles and Elders of the-Church of Ieruſalem,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.17 <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.2 <hi>Reve.</hi> 22, 18 <hi>Act.</hi> 5, 10,</note> who being aſſembled together did profeſſe it to be a tempting of God to lay ſuch a yok on the diſciples necks, as the obſerving of the Iewiſh ceremonies, which being vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to do, it is uuch more vnlawfull to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe and impoſe any other. And therefore the ſayd aſſembly of the Apoſtles &amp; Elders concluded to lay no greater burden vpon the diſciples, then to abſtaine from ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary things as either were ſimply evil in them ſelues, as fornication,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 15, 8 19, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> or elſe euill in reſpect of offence, as meate offered to Idols, blood and things ſtrangled.</p>
            <p>Now to proceed. firſt it is ſaid of this Beaſt. That hee did riſe up out of the ſea, By his riſing vp was foreſhewd that the Antichriſtian policie ſhould ariſe from a poore and meane eſtate to great riches and honour in the world, which we and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer generations have ſeene to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt fulfilled. For dayes there were when the Churches of Chriſt both Miniſters and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97365:6"/>people were hated, deſpiſed, and perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted in the world; ſpoiled of their goods, made gazing ſtocks and wonders, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted with all kinde of cruelty, as hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries both ſacred and humane do abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpecifie and declare. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of himſelf and his fellow-bretheren the Miniſters of the Goſpell, that they were as men appointed to death: and in the account of the world, as the filth, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe, and of-ſcouring of all things. But ſince this beaſtly generation hath ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Church, and under the titles of Miniſters of the Goſpell, and the Biſhops ouer Gods people, have found meanes by little and little to riſe up, and to exalt themſelves over the Nations, and to bring the multitudes, and peoples, and Nations, and Tongues, under their Iuriſdiction, rule and Dominion,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev</hi> 18 3 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 7.</note> and they have ſo riſen up, that they are become the great men of the earth, and are waxed rich through the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of their delicacies. This my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of iniquity was working in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles time, for there were then crept into the Church thoſe that deſired worldly pompe and promotion, and were not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with the portion of the Lords He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritage,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97365:6"/>but their ambitious deſires could not then be ſatisfied, there was a let in the way that hindered it, which lets being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, their purpoſes (ſoone after) took effect, fitly therefore is this generation ſaid to riſe up (in reſpect of thoſe whoſe ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours they boaſt themſelves to be.) The former hold no certaine dwelling places, but were expoſed to hunger, thirſt, cold, nakedneſſe, buffetings, &amp;c. But theſe lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter have their Lordly Houſes, warlike Caſtles, and Princelike Palaces, they have their Rents, Revenues, and abundance of riches, in great exceſſe, they are pompouſly arrayed in ſtately Robes and rich apparell, they rule like Lords over the people, and have power to aflict all that will not beare the yoke of their Dominion, thus is this generation riſen vp and exalted as all may ſee that liſt to minde it.</p>
            <p>The Place from whence this Beaſt is ſaid to riſe up, is the ſea, The naturall ſea wee know is the gathering together of many waters, Gen. 1.9. 10. A Like thing muſt that be out of which this beaſt was to riſe, But in the 17. Chapter. Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, and nations, peoples, and Tongues, are reſembled by waters, therefore the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97365:7"/>gathering together of ſuch into one body politike, may rightly be reſembled by the Sea. Thus then the truth ſtandeth, By the riſing up of this Beaſt out of the Sea, was foreſhewed, that thoſe many waters (that is, the people, and multitudes, and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Tongues, not onely under the Romane Empire: but moſt nations and people of the World) being gathered into one Sea, or Eccleſiaſticall State, ſhould breed and bring forth this Monſter.</p>
            <p>For they being of two contrary ſorts, the ſeed of the Serpent, and the ſeed of the Woman, Children of the Kingdom, and children of the wicked; unto the one ſort the Word of God (in the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof) is the ſavour of life unto life, unto the other ſort it is the ſavour of death unto death. The one ſort feare God, and will obey him rather then man; The other feare and reverence the arme of fleſh, more then they do the living God. Theſe (as light and darkneſſe) being contrary one to another; the one being of Chriſt, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Belial; how therefore ſhould they in things concerning God and Chriſt, Faith and Religion, agree together?</p>
            <p>Thoſe which be of God, cannot but
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97365:7"/>witneſſe againſt thoſe that be of the world, becauſe their deeds are evill. Thoſe which are of the world, are heady, high-minded, proud boaſters, wiſe in their own conceit, and therefore ſcorne to be rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and hate to be reformed. Theſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing together in the world as Wheat and Tares in one field; and as Sheep and Goats in one Flock; the true end of the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration of the Word of God had been to call and ſeparate the one from the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the precious from the vile, beleevers from infidels. But notwithſtanding, this generation thought it to be wiſdom to take a contrary courſe, namely, to bring all people of all ſorts to be one Church, and likewiſe unto uniformity in Religion. And becauſe it could not be effected by the Word of God (that ſword of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit) they procured the help of worldly governours to bring it to paſſe by their power and command. By which device and policie theſe many waters, that is, the Nations and people have been gathered into one Church, and Eccleſiaſticall body politike, here repreſented by the Sea, and have been brought to uſe all one order or worſhip, ſervice, and government.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:97365:8"/>
            <p>But this conformitie not being procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red through love, but conſtrained by feare, was but an humane deviſe, and worldly po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, and no divine Inſtitution, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore could not be upholden, maintained, and continued by the Word of God, and the adminiſtration of a ſerviceable Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery; but by the over-ruling power of a Lordly Prelacie, whereupon it was thought meet that Synods or Counſels of the chiefeſt of the Prelates and Cleargie of divers Dominions ſhould be gathered together to make Laws and Canons, which all men ſhould be conſtrained by penall Laws to obſerve and yeeld obedience un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and ſo peace and unitie might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved and kept amongſt them. And in ſhort time it came to paſſe, that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever theſe Synods or Counſels did agree upon, and ſet down, (how falſe ſoever) was to be held Canonicall, and thoſe that contradicted the ſame, were therefore caſt out and condemned as Heretikes. This was the manner and the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the riſing of this Beaſt out <hi>of this turbulent Sea.</hi> And here by the way obſerve,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 1.17</note> That <hi>every good giving, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect gift is from above, from the Father of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97365:8"/>lights:</hi> But this Beaſt is from the Sea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath, not from above, and therefore not belonging to the kingdome of Chriſt, But an adverſary and enimie thereof.</p>
            <p>Of this Beaſt it is ſaid, that he had 7, heads, a thing which is monſtrous in nature, And therefore by this wasforeſhewed that the dominion repreſented by this beaſt ſhould be a monſtrous dominion.</p>
            <p>Concerning theſe heads, let this be conſidered, That the whole ſtate or ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Antichriſtian Sea, is of two ſorts of people; the one ſort they call the <hi>Cleargie,</hi> the other ſort the <hi>Layetie.</hi> Of theſe; the <hi>Cleargie</hi> are as heads and guides to direct and go before, and the <hi>Laietie</hi> as the body, or rather the tayle, to follow after. Again, by the ſame policy, their Cleargie are ſorted into ſeven orders or degrees, namely (to ſpeake in their lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage) 1. <hi>Iamtores ſets oſtiarij.</hi> 2. <hi>Lecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</hi> 3. <hi>Exorciſtie,</hi> 4. <hi>Acolithi.</hi> 5. <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diaconi.</hi> 6. <hi>Diaconi.</hi> 7. <hi>Sacerdotes.</hi> Theſe are the ſeven orders of the Antichriſtian Cleargie. As for Popes, Cardinals, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarches, Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacous, &amp;c. they are titles of Dignity, and not of order. For the Pope is but a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97365:9"/>Prieſt concerning his orders, and when he ſtands at the Altar and faith Maſſe, he doth that as Prieſt, and not as a Pope, and ſo of all other degrees. This conſidered, it may well bee ſaid of the Anti-chriſtian Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue and State, that it is as a Monſter with ſeven heads. As for the Miniſters which God hath ordained to be in his Church, they are firſt Apoſtles, ſecondly Prophets, thirdly Teachers, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28, &amp;c. See alſo, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.6, 7, 1. <hi>&amp; Eph.</hi> 4, 11, 12, 13. And theſe onely were given for the gathering together of the <hi>Saints, for the work of the Ministery, and for the edification of the body of Christ.</hi> Not ſome to have a bunch of Keys, with a charge of the doors of this or that Temple or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedrall Church; Another to have a book to read to the people things which neither he nor they did underſtand. A third to have a Book of Conjurations or Charmes, with charge to read them, or ſay by heart, to ſuch as were diſtracted of their wits, or poſſeſſed with Divels, and to put their hands upon them. A fourth, to have a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per or Wax-candle, with a Candleſtick to carry before the Prieſts and Deacons, in doing their ſervice.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:97365:9"/>
            <p>A fift, to recive of the people obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and offerings, and to deliver them to the Deacon to carry to the Altar, to read the Epiſtle, and to ſtand by the Preiſt while he was ſaying the Maſſe,</p>
            <p>A ſixth to be the Biſhops ſpie and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligencer to informe him of ſuch as be irregular, and obſerve not their orders, to read the Goſpell, attend the Prieſt at the Altar, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>A ſeventh, to conſecrate the Hoaſt, as they call it, and then to offer it as a ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice propitiatory for the quick and dead.</p>
            <p>Theſe are not they which God hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to be in the Church; But theſe are they whereof the Antichriſtian Cleargie conſiſteth, for whoſoever is one of that Cleargie, is one of theſe ſeven orders, be he Pope, Prelate, or elſe whatſoever, and to note and foreſhew this point of policy, this Beaſt which IOHN ſaw had ſeven heads.</p>
            <p>If any ſhall thinke this to be a vaine, frivolous, and ſtrange interpretation to underſtand, by the ſeven heads of the Beaſt, theſe ſeven order of the Cleargie, as thinking thoſe heads to betoken things
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97365:10"/>of greater note and importance: Let ſuch conſider, what account and reckoning is made of ſuch perſons as have received the Sacraments of Orders, and holy ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the kingdome of the Beaſt, and they ſhall finde the interpretation not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent, but very agreeable. For a time there was ſince the writing of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, Matiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conen, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum. Can.</hi> 9.10</note> when the meaneſt ſhrimp that was within theſe holy Orders (as they call them) was held to be of that dignity, that the chiefeſt and worthieſt ſecular Iudge in a Kingdom was held unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy to judge or cenſure them for any treſpaſſe or fact, how notorious, wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and manifeſt ſoever, becauſe they had received holy Tonſure, and were thereby conſecrated and ſet apart unto God, to be his portion and heritage, and to pray for the people, and therefore were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from all ſecular juriſdiction and power, ſuch was their dignity accounted to be, and ſtill is, where that kingdom pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaileth, and hath the dominion: yea, ever in this Land that quarrell hath coſt the King his Crown: as it is to be ſeene in the Hiſtories of the Reign of King IOHN and not his Crown onely, but his life
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97365:10"/>alſo. Now if the meaneſt of them be above the dominion of any King or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Iudge, and ſecular Iudges be the heads of the people, whom God hath appointed to beare rule over them, well may theſe be ſaid to be as heads in the kingdom of the Beaſt, wherein theſe ſhavelings are holden to be ſo holy and high in dignity and degree.</p>
            <p>As this Beaſt which <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw had ſeven <hi>heads,</hi> ſo likewiſe it had ten <hi>hornes,</hi> whereby was foreſhewed, that as the Kings of the Medes and Perſians were ſhewed and repreſented to <hi>Daniel,</hi> by the two hornes of the Beaſt which he ſaw in his viſion, ſo the Kings of many Kingdomes ſhould be as garders and defenders of the Antichriſtian king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and ſtate.</p>
            <p>And that this Scripture hath been ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled to the uttermoſt by the Kings of the Nations, is ſo manifeſt, that none can be ignorant of it, that are of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and experience. And it was juſt with the Lord to make the Kings of the earth vaſſals to this Beaſt, becauſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived not the love of the truth, but took pleaſure in urighteouſneſſe; they would
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97365:11"/>not forſake their ſins to live godlily, righteouſly, and ſoberly (as all muſt do, that will attaine ſalvation) but they would live after their luſts, and for their ſins they would make ſatisfaction by building of Churches and Monaſteries, &amp;c. and endowing them with Lands, Rents, and other Revenews, by means whereof thoſe which traded like Merchants in thoſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny waters, the kingdom of the Beaſt grew rich and wealthy, and became the great men of the earth.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, <hi>John</hi> faith of the Beaſt that he ſaw, that it was like a <hi>Leopard,</hi> &amp;c. By the reſemblance and likeneſſe of a <hi>Leopard</hi> was ſignified that this Beaſt ſhould be foule and full of ſpots, as is ſhewed in the 18 Chapter: <hi>Babylon is become the habitation of Divels, and the hold of foule ſpirits, and the Cage of every unclean and hatefull Bird.</hi> The filthineſſe of this Beaſt is apparant, in that he doth by force and Armes compell all ſorts of wicked and ungodly people to be of his ſociety, and refuſeth none but the godly, therefore fitly was he thus prefigured.</p>
            <p>Secondly, by the quallity and diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Leopard, was ſignified that
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97365:11"/>this Generation ſhould be ſubtile and crafty in getting their prey. They boaſt themſelves to be the Church and Spouſe of Chriſt; but if it be ſo, whence then had they that infinite ſtore and abundance of worldly wealth and riches, wherewith they exceed in deliciouſneſſe of living? This was not the condition of Chriſt and his Diſciples, the Lord himſelfe had not whereon to lay his head, but in that reſpect was more deſtitute then Foxes which have holes, and then Birds which have neſts: his Diſciples wanted gold and ſilver, and had no certaine dwelling place; whence therefore had this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration their Lands, Livings, and Lordſhips? Their Caſtles, Mannors, Houſes, and Princely Palaces? It will be ſaid of the donation and gift of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, Kings, and other great States, and of the charitable devotion of all ſorte of people: But how were people brought to be ſo full handed to this generation? To bring this about, much ſlight, craft, and nimbleneſſe of with was uſed; firſt, people were made to believe, that what they gave to the Church, was to the maintenance of the Miniſtery of the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97365:12"/>Goſpell, and for the comfort and reliefe of the poore, and therefore ſhould be a ſacrifice ſo well pleaſing to God, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritorious, as that it ſhould receive great reward at his hands, herewith the mindes of religious and devout people was ſo much moved, that they thought nothing too much to give to the Church, by means whereof Churches began to grow rich. Secondly, people were made to believe that the worſhiping of Images and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks of Saints, and building of Churches, Chappels, Oratories, &amp;c. and endowing them with Lands, Tenements, Parſonage and Vicarage houſes, &amp;c. was an effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall way to have favour with the Saints, and to procure their praiers and interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for them: By theſe and ſuch like means this wylie and crafty generation deluded the people, and made themſelves rich, and robbed Chriſt of his honour, who onely is our Advocate to God. And furthermore, they gathered in heaps of wealth, by Maſſes, Pilgrimages, Purſſe-penance, Offerings, and ſuch like Merchandiſes, wherein their ſubtilty and craft was prefigured by a Leopard; a Beaſt ſubtile by nature, whoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97365:12"/>is to lie in waite for her prey, and ſlilie to catch it as the Cat doth the Mouſ<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and in that reſpect doth well reſemble the Antichriſtian Clergie, that ſubtill genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But further it is added, that <hi>the feete of this Beast were as the feete of a Beare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Leopard is more nimble to catch then the Beare, but the Beare is more ſtrong and eager to hold faſt that which he hath ſeaſed vpon, then is the Leopard<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> both theſe properties this generation hath, nimble to catch and greedy to hold, they catch by ſlight, But hold by force. and therefore in catching reſemble the Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pard, but in faſt holding the feete of a Beare.</p>
            <p>To this it is added, that <hi>the mouth of this Beaſt was as the mouth of a Lion.</hi> And by this another propertie of the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Clergie was foreſhewed, for as the Lion when he hath taken his prey roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vpon it, at whoſe roaring the Beaſts tremble: So this generation being thus exalted and made rich, and have gotten their prey, they terrifie the ſmall Beaſts of the Forreſts, roaring with curſes, and excommunications againſt, be he Prince
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97365:13"/>or Peſant, that ſhall preſume to part ſtakes with them, or meddle with their prey, or diminiſh their portion, but an Egge or an Onion. That theſe be the properties of this Generation needs no proof, it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt by daily experience.</p>
            <p>Here therefore we may learne what to eſteem and judge of the Antichriſtian Cleargie, together with thoſe Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, People, Nations, and Tongues, out of which they have ſprung, and over which they are ſet and ſupported; name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they are a monſtrous and beaſtly Generation, excelling in craft, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, pride, cruelty, and all ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; and therefore not to be eſteemed, as they boaſt themſelves to be a holy Catholike Church, and Spouſe of Chriſt, which cannot erre, &amp;c. And by this we may ſee how lamentably the Nations have been deluded and led into errour and ungodlineſſe, by their guides and leaders.</p>
            <p>Now it followeth, that unto this Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter the <hi>Dragon</hi> gave his power, and his Throne, and <hi>great authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is declared of whom the Prelates and Clergie have received their ſpirituall Lordſhips, power, authority, and juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97365:13"/>to deviſe and make ſpirituall Laws and Canons, to erect ſpirituall Courts, and create Officers to beare rule, and exerciſe dominion over the Nations, even from the Divell: they have not any lawfull authority from God, but an uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped authority from the Divell, whoſe inſtruments they are, to advance his kingdom, and to perſecute the Saints, which obey God rather then men,</p>
            <p>And here we may obſerve that they are rightly called ſpirtuall Lords, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe originally they proceed from that prince that ruleth in the aire, the ſpirit that worketh in the children of unbeliefe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but withall, in ſtead of ſpirituall Lords, Laws, Courts and Officers, call them ſpirituall wickedneſſes, and ſo we give them their right titles: and being ſuch, if we will fight the good fight of faith, we muſt by witneſſing what they be, wraſtle againſt them, and not ſubmit unto them, but ſtand faſt in that liberty wherewith Chriſt hath made us free, and not be intangled with any yoke of bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage: and that we may wraſtle and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile, we muſt take unto us the whole <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour of God, Epheſ.</hi> 6.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:97365:14"/>
            <p>Further, <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith, <hi>that he ſaw one of the heads of the Beaſt as it were wounded to death, and his deadly wound was healed, and all the world wondred after the Beaſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this Head, which was as it were wounded to death, was ſignified the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viving of Prieſthood, the myſterie whereof, in few words, is this. <hi>The wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of iniquity in this Antichristian king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, having ordained this order of mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, called Priesthood (whether it were in imitation of the Iews, or Heathen, it is doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) but certain it is, that becauſe it wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted externall ſacrifices, it came ſhort both of the Iewiſh Priesthood, and alſo of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, ſo that it was a lame and wounded Prieſthood, and was not reſpected.</hi> In time it came to paſſe that they found out a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice (as is to bee ſeene in their Maſſe-book) which was the tranſubſtantiating of Bread into Wine, into the very Body and Blood of Chriſt, really and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially (as they uſe to ſpeak and teach) and being ſo tranſubſtantiated to offer it up unto God, a ſacrifice propitiatory both for quick and dead. Thus the wounded head of Prieſthood was cured and revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and ſo became the worlds wonder,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97365:14"/>as now it followeth to be declared, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as <hi>Iohn</hi> here witneſſeth:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And all the world wondred after the Beast.</hi> That is, the people of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions having this Prieſthood ſet over them, and commended unto them to be of ſuch power and dignity, as that they could make them a viſible God, not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to behold with their eyes, and look upon, but alſo to eate, and that their Maker and Redeemer, to their everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſalvation: And being ſo effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally deluded, as that they beleeved theſe lies, hereupon they wondred, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed the Beaſt. Well might they wonder to ſee bread, and taſte bread, where was no bread; and to ſee wine, and taſte wine, where was no wine (for ſo were they made to believe) and to eate fleſh, and drink bloud, and yet neither to ſee nor take fleſh nor bloud: this was a wonder to wonder at; and who would not follow him for a guide, that had power to worke ſuch wonders?</p>
            <p>But they did not onely follow the Beaſt, as the Iews did Chriſt, when they ſaw his miracles, <hi>But they worſhipped the Dragon which gave power unto the Beaſt, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97365:15"/>they worſhipped the Beaſt, ſaying, who is like unto the Beaſt? Who is able to make warre with him?</hi> To worſhip, is to heare and obey; and by worſhipping the Dragon was ſhewed, that they wholly addicted themſelves to be directed and ruled by the Beaſt, whom the Dragon uſed as his inſtrument to work his will, and to whom he had given authority and power to that end: thus originally they worſhiped the Divell. Secondly, they worſhipped the Beaſt, as being the inſtrument of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell, and they became ſubjects in all things obedient unto the Beaſt, as being of ſuch holineſſe and truth, as that it could not erre, nor deceive others, and of ſuch pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, as what they looſed on earth, was looſed in heaven; and what they bound in earth, was bound in heaven; and therefore ſuch a power as had no match or peere, ſo that they boaſted and ſaid of it, <hi>Who is like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Beast?</hi> As <hi>David</hi> conſidering the power and wonderfull workes of God, ſaith; <hi>Who is like unto the Lord?</hi> So do the Nations boaſt of this Beaſt, ſaying: <hi>Who is like unto the Beaſt?</hi> And further they ſaid of him, <hi>Who is able to make warre with him?</hi> As if they ſhould ſay,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:97365:15"/>This our holy Mother hath power to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate, and deliver to Satan, all (of what eſtate, condition, degree, ſoever they be) that will not heare her voice, beare her yoke, and be ruled by her: Who therefore is able to make war with her? that is, make his party good againſt this our holy Mother. Of ſuch admiration was this Beaſt in the earth; thus hath the world thought, and ſpoken of her.</p>
            <p>And moreover, there was <hi>given unto this Beaſt a mouth, ſpeaking great things, and blaſphemies, and power was given him to make</hi> 42 <hi>moneths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the mouth is the means and inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment whereby men do declare their mindes, ſo this Beaſt had a mouth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and utter her minde; by which mouth was ſignified a miniſtery of falſe prophets, and lying ſpirits, namely, Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours, School-men, Monkes, Fryers, and all ſorts of their Preachers, who teach for doctrines the commandements of the Beaſt, and declare and utter the minde and will of the Beaſt, as being equall to Gods Word, this their Canons, Laws, Books and Monuments, do mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly witneſſe.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:97365:16"/>
            <p>The effect of that which this mouth ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth, is noted to be <hi>great things, and blaſphemies.</hi> They boaſt of this Beaſt, that ſhe is the holy Catholike Church Militant, the Mother of all rrue belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers: the chaſte Spouſe of Chriſt, the Pillar and ground of Truth, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre, &amp;c. And that all which will have God to be their Father, muſt have her to be their Mother. Finally, that out of her lap and communion, there is no ſalvation. Theſe and many other ſuch great things ſpeaketh the mouth of this Beaſt, which are indeed great things, and being ſo ſpoken, are great blaſphemies. For is it not great blaſphemie to call that Holy, which is moſt abominable? To call her the Mother of all true Beleevers, which is the mother of fornications, and of all abominations? To call that the Pillar and ground of Truth, which hath corrupted the earth with her errours and fornications, and cauſed all Nations to drink of the wine of the wrath thereof? To ſay there is no ſalvation but in her fellowſhip, whoſe end and judgement is to go to deſtruction? Beware of falſe Prophets, and teachers of lies, for ſuch
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97365:16"/>are the mouth of this Beaſt.</p>
            <p>And it is further to be minded, that it is ſaid of this Beaſt, that the mouth which ſhe had, was given her; for had this Beaſt no more to maintaine this mouth, then ſhe hath of her own by diſcent and heritage, ſhe could not have ſo many to ſpeak for her as ſhe hath: But Emperous and Kings, Princes and Nobles, and other great ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, became benefactours to this Beaſt, giving unto her Lands and Tenements, Rents and Revenews, to maintaine this mouth to utter great things, and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and more then this, <hi>Power was given him to act, or make, two and forty moneths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the better underſtanding of this point, let this be conſidered: In the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian kingdom they have a rule how to proceed in every cauſe, but not given them of God, but of their own making, which they commonly call the Canon Law; concerning which Law, here we may learne by whom it was made, and how long it was in making. Theſe Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets uſurp the name of the Church of Chriſt, but the true Church is the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Chriſt, and being the Kingdom of Chriſt, it hath him onely for Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giver,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97365:17"/>they therefore which under the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of the Church preſume to make laws, are fitly and worthily reſembled by a beaſt, for what is more vnreaſonable then for thoſe whoſe greateſt dignity, glory and happines, conſiſteth in hearing, obeying, and adminiſtring of gods word, to fall from this, and Lucifer-like to exalt and oppoſe themſelves againſt their Maker, as though they were wiſer and iuſter then God: and to adde unto his Teſtament Which is ſuficient to inſtruct us in all Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and to make the man of God per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect in every good worke: and to take from the ſame Teſtament at their pleaſure which is not lawfull to do to any mans Teſtament, without great offence and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice, as the Apoſtle ſheweth, Ga. 3.15 yet thit is the way wherein thoſe great doers, the authors of the Canon Law haue walked. It is ſaid of thoſe Actors, <hi>that Power was given them, &amp;c.</hi> Where firſt we may obſerv, that of themſelves they had not this power, for then it could not haue beene ſaid to be given them, but given them it was; it is therefore to be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, Who was the giver: Not Chriſt he gave his diſciples no power to make Laws,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97365:17"/>but gave them charge to teath belivers to obſerve all things whatſoever he had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them, it is certain therefore that this power was given them, not by God but by men: namely by Kings and Princes, for the ſtates and degrees of men conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, it is plaine, that none can give power to make Lawes but ſuch as be Soveraignes; by ſuch therefore this power to make Lawes was given unto this Beaſt. But what ſhould move Soveraignes to give power to Biſhops and Miniſters to make Lawes for the Church? Nothing verily but blind devotion; for they being ignorant of God and of his Word, thought it the beſt way to keep peace and vnity in the Church. Whereas indeed it was the cauſe of ſtrife and diſſention, and at length by that meanes iniquity was eſtabliſhed for a Law, and Gods Word wholy reiected and caſt aſide as vnmeet for Lay men to vſe. Now as in all lawfull proceedings, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are Gods miniſters, in Gods ſtead vnto their ſubiects and people, ſo in giuing this power to this Beaſt, they are the Dragons miniſters, and inſtruments. Whereas it is ſaid that power was given unto the Beaſt to make, but it is not noted what ſhould
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97365:18"/>be made, it argueth that the things made are of that nature and qualitie that they are not worthy of any name, the makers them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves uſe to call their Acts, Canons, Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions and Lawes, but falfly, for if they were ſuch indeed, then men might have ſome good vſe of them, but that no man can have, therefore it is but falſhood and deceit ſo to name them: It is like the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of one carved Image, S. <hi>Peter,</hi> another S, <hi>Paul,</hi> another S. <hi>Iohn</hi> &amp;c. that is to name things that they be not, and that is to lie.</p>
            <p>In that it is ſaid, that power was given unto the beaſt to make 12. Moneths, It ſheweth that the Beaſts time is limited, and ſeeing that the time is limited, we muſt finde that the time of making of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church agreeth with this ſtint, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can be ſure that it is the Beaſt, here repreſented, wherefore conſider that the eccleſiaſtical ſtate began to make about the yeare of our Lord, 304. (the Ancyran coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell being the firſt, whoſe conſtitutions tooke the effect and force of Law, (And made not an end of making vntill the year 1564. the Counſell of Trent being the laſt wherein the Beaſt acted the laſt act of this
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97365:18"/>making, and fulfilled the meaſure of that iniquitie, and therefore is now to receaue judgment &amp; condemnation from the Lord, as is hereafter in this propheſie declared, So that if we account a yeare for a day, and thirtie dayes for a month, it will amount to 1260, dayes which is the juſt ſum of 42. moneths, that this Beaſt was a making, which is a ſtrong argument, that by this Beaſt was ſignified the eccleſiaſticall eſtate or Catholicke Church, as is ſhewed before, page 2.</p>
            <p>Further it is ſaid of the Beaſt, that he opened <hi>his mouth in blaſphemy against God, to blaſpheme his name, and his tabernacle, and them that dwell in heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In that this Beaſt, by the miniſtery of falſe Prophets and Teachers, as by her mouth hath ſeduced the Nations, and made them believe, That God by the miniſtery of his holy Apoſtles and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, hath not left us a ſure rule ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient rule of faith, in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but that the want thereof muſt be ſupplied with unwritten verities, the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of Ancient Fathers, determinations of Counſels, and the Popes Decretals, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe all people would run into confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:97365:19"/>it may truly be ſaid, that ſhe hath opened her mouth untoblaſphemy againſt God, Firſt the eternall who hath created all things, and for whoſe wills ſake all things are and were created, To be but a rude and groſſe beginner of a worke, which he hath left and given up for vaine man to finiſh and make perfect. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, if there be particular laws left out of the Scriptures, for want of which all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple would run into confuſion, then God hath not ſhewed himſelfe to be a God of order. Thirdly, the World of God is not ſufficient to make the man of God perfect, in every good work, as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles ſaith. But thus to think, is a horrible errour. Thus to ſpeak, is wicked blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, and thus to teach, is helliſh ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity. For how will it ſtand with the glory of God, and of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, not to give unto his people a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Law, and ſure Teſtimony, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto they might truſt, and wherein they might reſt and live by faith, but muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon other men, to ſee as it were with their eyes, &amp; not with their own, and ſo hold their faith, in reſpect of other mens perſons, to belieue as they believe, &amp;c.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:97365:19"/>as though Gods people (their Leaders ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted) were not reaſonable creatures, but as beaſts without underſtanding: But bleſſed be our God, we have a ſure Word of the Prophets, which is as a light ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in a darke place, whereunto we ſhall do well if we take heed. Gods people have no need of unwritten verities, mens precepts and traditions; They have ſurer Lights to walk by, then the writings of the School-men, and other Writers of ancient times; They have ſurer Rules, and righter Teſtimonies, wherby to decide and end controverſies and doubts, then the deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of Counſels, and Popes decrees, and they which ſpeak to the contrary, open their mouth to balſpheme againſt God. Concerning blaſpheming the Name of God, amongſt other attributes or titles whereby he is ſet forth unto us, he is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the <hi>Holy one of Iſrael,</hi> and the High Prieſt in <hi>Iſrael</hi> did beare this inſcription upon his forehead graven in gold, <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to the Lord.</hi> Firſt, therefore we may truly and boldly ſay of the Lord, that <hi>Holy</hi> is his Name. Secondly, we may likewiſe truly and boldly affirme, that to give the title of <hi>Holineſſe</hi> unto any unholy prophane
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97365:20"/>and abominable thing, is to blaſpheme the name of God: But thus the Beaſt hath done many and ſundry waies. They aſcribe <hi>Holineſſe</hi> unto their Antichriſtian orders, and Prieſthood to their Idolatrous Maſſe, to their exorciſed or conjured Bread, Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Oyle, Tapers, Aſhes, Veſtures, Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and many other implements in and by al which they blaſpheme the name of God.</p>
            <p>And as they blaſpheme the Name of God; So likewiſe the blaſpheme his Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, That is to ſay, the true viſible Church of Chriſt under the Goſpel, which is the place of Gods, preſence, which he hath choſen to put his Name there, where two or three, or more are gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Name of Chriſt, there is Chriſt preſent, and where Chriſt is preſent, there hath God put his Name, there he is to be ſought, and there he may be found, and there is his Tabernacle. To come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Name of Chriſt, is when Gods people joyne themſelves together in a ſpirituall body politike, ſeparated from the common multitudes of known unbeleevers, to the end to meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the mutuall edification and comfort one of another, by doctrine,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:97365:20"/>breaking of bread, and prayer, and to practiſe all other Ordinances of Chriſt ſet down in his Teſtament, as they ſhall haue occaſion: and to Companies of Beleevers, having ſuch fellowſhip and communion one with another, the title of the Churches of Chriſt doth (in our uſe of ſpeech) properly and of right belong: but for beleevers to do this apart by themſelves, is adjudged contempt of authority, factious, novelty, making of Conventicles, and unlawfull Aſſemblies, dangerous to the State, and not to be ſuffered in any Kingdom or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and ſo they blaſpheme the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of God in a high degree, as if Gods people were a company of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly rebels, and wicked conſpiratours; but the righteous Lord will in due time viſit his people, and rebuke his enemies.</p>
            <p>And on the other ſide, for Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple now to deny the kingdom of the Beaſt; that is, (as they call it) the holy Catholike Church Militant, to be the true Church of Chriſt; To refuſe to partake and communicate with them in their abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, deluſions, and unlawful works of darknes, is adjudged diſobedience, ſchiſme
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97365:21"/>and contempt of the power and authorty of the Church; To ſpeak againſt their proceedings, ſedition, diſturbance of the peace of the Church, hereſie, impiety, and what not? Thus they adorne the Harlot, which corrupteth the earth with her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nications, with the title of the Church, and Spouſe of Chriſt, and Tabernacle of God, and ſo blaſpheme the Tabernecle of God, as if it were not a communion of Saints, by calling and profeſſion, but an ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitation of Divels, an hold of foule Spirits, and a Cage of every unclean and hatefull Bird.</p>
            <p>Further, it is ſaid of the Beaſt, that it did <hi>blaſpheme thoſe that dwelt in heaven,</hi> that is, the <hi>Saints</hi> departed this life.</p>
            <p>Thoſe that dwell in heaven, are then blaſphemed, when it is ſaid of them, that they take it as an honour done unto them, when we make them our Patrons, build them Temples, ſet up their Images, offer and pray unto them, and make them Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atours between Chriſt and us, for by this they are made, not onely Idols, but alſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourers and chief maintainers of Idolatry: They are alſo blaſphemed when the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine which they taught and practiſed, is
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97365:21"/>condemned for hereſie, or when erronious doctrines, vaine traditions, ſuperſtitious rites, ceremonies and cuſtomes are fathered upon them, as received from them by Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, as unwritten verities, but the world hath been brought to believe that Saints in heaven might by theſe means be as it were bought and ſould, between Prieſt and people, wherein they have been high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly blaſphemed.</p>
            <p>Moreover, it is ſaid, <hi>that it was given to the Beaſt to make warre with the Saints, and to overcome them: and power was given him over all Kindreds, and Tongues, and Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Warre is made with the Saints, when they are accuſed to Rulers and Governors, to be Heretikes Schiſmaticks, wicked and ungodly perſons; and they may then be ſaid to be overcome, whem their accuſers are juſtified, and they condemned, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to this, this Scripture hath been ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled and verified. Great and of long continuance have been the warres which the Beaſt hath made with the Saints, and many have been the victories of this kinde which the Beaſt hath had againſt them, as the Hiſtories, and other records of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions do plentifully witnes.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:97365:22"/>
            <p>It was given to the Beaſt to make warre with the Saints, when Rulers and Governours gave way to the Beaſt to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe and make laws at their own pleaſure, concerning Religion, and the worſhip of God, and then to condemne for Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, and evill doers, all that would not obſerve thoſe Laws. How free and forward Rulers and Governours have been to give ſuch power unto the Beaſt, they themſelves have felt by long and wofull experience: for much woe hath the Beaſt wrought (not to the poore and meaner ſort of the Saints onely, but) even to Emperours and Kings, and all degrees of people, and therefore it is ſaid in the words follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that power was given unto this Beaſt over every Kindred, Tongue and Nation: So that the exaltation thereof was ſuch, as to be a Father above all fathers to every Kindred; a Lord above all Lords to every Tongue; a King above all Kings to every Nation. Thus was this Beaſt exalted and ſate as a Queen triumphing over them, having all of all degrees brought in bondage unto her Dominion, which was a juſt recompence upon their heads,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97365:22"/>that gave ſuch power unto this Beaſt: yet ſee how the world was herein deluded, they were not captives againſt their wills, but in blind devotion, had this Beaſt in moſt high reverence, as being a devine power ordained and given by God, and not from the Dragon, Thus did the Lord give them over to be deluded by this Beaſt, as a juſt reward of their vngodlynes, in that they receaued not the loue of the truth, but tooke pleaſure in vnrighteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>Further it is declared in the words fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, <hi>That all that dwell vpon the earth must worſhip him,</hi> (that is the Beaſt) <hi>whoſe, names are not written in the booke of the life of the Lamb ſlayne from the foundation of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>by thoſe that dwell on the earth is ment thoſe that have ſet their habitation there, and chooſe rather to enioy the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie of the world and pleſures of ſinne, together with the Beaſt, then to ſufffer affliction for the truth, and for witneſſing againſt the Beaſt: theſe are they that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him, that is, receaue their precepts and rules, for their doctrine and whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome inſtuction, and obſerve their ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and Lawes as perfect rules of eqi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97365:23"/>and righteouſneſſe, caſting the word of God declared in the holy ſcriptures, be hind their backes, and treading his Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances vnder their feete, making farre more conſcience not to eate an Egge on Friday, then to ſteale, or to commit adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, But of ſuch it is ſaid, that their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes are not written in the Booke of life of the Lamb which was ſlaine from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world: That is, they are not of the number of Gods Elect and Chooſen in Chriſt, and given vnto him for his por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and heritage, whoſe condition is to be hated, deſpiſed, perſecuted, and afflicted in the world, for righteouſnes ſake, in whom the Lamb Chriſt Jeſus, as in his members hath been ſlaine ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world: which condition, thoſe which cannot brook and endure, but count it a pleaſure to live deliciouſly for a ſeaſon, and take delight to enjoy the pleaſures of ſin, may thereby be diſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, not to have their names written in the Book of life.</p>
            <p>Concerning theſe things it is added, <hi>If any man have an eare, let him heare,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As if it ſhould be ſaid, few there be which have an eare to heare theſe things:
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97365:23"/>For who can indure to heare that Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, which they account to be ſpirituall, holy, and heavenly, to bee compared to a Beaſt, ugly in forme, and horrible and monſtrous in nature; Who can endure to heare that Power, that Throne, and that authority, which they believe to be of God, to be ſaid and affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be of the Dragon, that old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, the Divell, and Satan? Who will believe that a righteous God would give way to his enemies, the workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, ſo farre to prevaile, and ſo long time, as for many hundred years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to delude the Nations, to bring them into bondage, and to keepe them in ſlavery? And that a few poore deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed people, of no reckoning in the world, here one, and there another, ſhould ſee more, and be wiſer then all the great Clarkes, wiſe Counſellours, mighty Princes, and all the Nobles of the earth? Who (I ſay) hath an eare to heare theſe things, and not be moved to fret in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and to gnaſh his teeth at the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of them?</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding all this, and more, let him that hath an eare heare, for times
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97365:24"/>and ſeaſons will change: a time will come (as the verſe following doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare) when theſe great workers of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity ſhall be ſubdued and trodden under foot.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that leadeth into captivitie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 20,</note> 
               <hi>ſhall go into captivitie, he that killeth with the ſword muſt be killed with the ſword, here is the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience and faith of the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is ſhewed the juſtice of God, who will recompence unto the wicked, according to the works of their hands, as they have meaſured unto others, it ſhall be meaſured unto them again; they ſhall reap the fruit of their unrighteouſneſſe to the full: Therefore the Saints and Servants of God ſhould here learne with patience to beare the Croſſe, becauſe the Lord will take their parts, and avenge their blood upon their enemies, and thoſe which with patience reſt upon the Lord. are here recorded for Saints. <hi>Here is the patience and faith of the Saints.</hi> As if it were ſaid, thoſe which patiently in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure affliction for the truth, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit their cauſe unto God, reſting faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully upon him, are thereby tryed and made manifeſt to the world, to bee the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97365:24"/>Saints and Servants of God, that in ſure hope of a time of refreſhing, chuſe to endure captivity and the ſword, rather then they will (to have peace with the world) together with the world worſhip the Beaſt.</p>
            <p>Thus much concerning the firſt part of this Chapter, and of that power and promotion which the Prelates and Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie crope up unto before the exaltation and ſupremacy of the Pope. The my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of whoſe iniquitie is next to be conſidered; <hi>To God be glorie for euer.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:97365:25"/>
               <head>THE SECOND PART OF the XIII. Chapter of the Revelation, beginning at the XI. verſe.</head>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>VERSE XI.</bibl> And I heheld another Beaſt comming up out of the earth, and he had two hornes like a Lamb, and he ſpake as a Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon.</q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>AS in the former part of this Chapter, the Prelacy and Clergie in generall, who under the title of the Catholike Church Militant, exalted themſelves to worke iniquity, and bring the Nations in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to captivity and bondage to their tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, were reſembled by a ſeven-headed Beaſt: ſo here after much ſtriving amongſt themſelves who ſhould be the chiefe and greateſt, not being content with former riches, honour, aad earthly promotion, but aſpiring higher, at laſt the Prelate of Rome in particular, attained to this title and dignity, to be Chriſts Vicar, <hi>Peters</hi> Succeſſour, and univerſall Biſhop; and under that Title pretended a fulneſſe of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97365:25"/>power and ſupremacie over all perſons and cauſes, and therefore is here reſembled and fore ſhewed by a Beaſt, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Firſt whereas it is ſaid of this Beaſt that it came out of the earth, thereby is ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the high degree and dignitie wherevnto the Prelates of Rome have aſpired, and exalted themſelves, is not from heaven, it is from the earth, earthly; it is a plant which our heavenly Father hath not planted, and therefore ſhall in the end be rooted out.</p>
               <p>Concerning the comming up of this Beaſt, it is to be minded, that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Word of God (of which ranke of men this Beaſt boaſteth himſelfe to be the chiefe) if they were in their right kinde, ſhould be as the Stars of Heaven, lights and guides unto others: But at the opening of the ſixth Seale, <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaw the Starres fall from Heaven to the Earth, as a fig-tree caſteth her greene figges when ſhe is ſhaken of a mighty winde; whereby was ſignified, that the Miniſters of the Word of God would in time degenerate and goe out of kinde; they would, contrary to the Apoſtles rule, ſet their affections on
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97365:26"/>earthly things, they would for filthy lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre make Merchandize of the people, and Word of God; they would gather riches, and grow wealthy by the wages of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſſe, and ſo become the great men of the earth: all which is fulfilled and come to paſſe, as all may ſee that are not willingly blinde.</p>
               <p>Among the reſt of the fallen Starres, to one was given the Key of the bottomleſſe pit, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9, 1. whereby was ſignified that power and preheminence ſhould be given to one of the fallen Stars above the reſt: which thing was effected &amp; came to paſſe, when <hi>Phocas</hi> being Emperour, he promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Boniface,</hi> then Prelate of <hi>Rome,</hi> to be univerſall Biſhop, and to have power and juriſdiction over all other Biſhops. Which thing when <hi>Phocas</hi> had done, this <hi>Abaddon</hi> King of <hi>Locuſts,</hi> with the reſt of the brood of the bottomleſſe pit that ſucceded him, who had the opening and ſhutting of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory at their pleaſure, ſo prevailed in time, that they exalted themſelves above Emperours and Kings, which thing they could never have done, had they not firſt beſotted the Nations in blinde devotion to impoveriſh themſelves to feed theſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:97365:26"/>Locuſts, under the Title of the Church, and in hope of meriting thereby, and to be releaſed from their ſins, and from the ſuppoſed paines of Purgatory: For had the Pope, that Prelate of <hi>Rome,</hi> been as deſtitute of worldly wealth, and as well furniſhed with ſpirituall grace, as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> were, when they went up into the Temple to pray, and healed the lame man, he had never ſet his foot upon the Emperours neck. For as much therefore as the Romiſh Prelate from a meane and lowly eſtate and degree in the world, hath crept up and been exalted above Kings and Emperours: and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worldly wealth and riches have been the means whereby he hath got the preheminence, very ſignificantly was this upſtart reſembled and prefigu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, by a Beaſt comming up out of the earth.</p>
               <p>Againe, it is ſaid of this Beaſt, that it had two Horns like the Lamb: By Hornes in the Scripture is uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſignified power and authoritie, and by the Lamb is meant CHRIST IESUS, who had all power in Heaven and earth given to him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18. So
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:97365:27"/>that hereby was ſhewed, that the Prelate of <hi>Rome</hi> would challenge and uſurpe great power and authority, which he perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the world doth belong unto him, as being Chriſts Vicar, and under this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence uſurpeth a twofold power and juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, both Civill and Eccleſiaſticall, not in earth onely, but in Heaven alſo; what he bindeth in earth, is bound in Heaven, and whom he will, he can releaſe from the paines of Purgatory, and place them in Heaven: Therefore in token of this his power, he is armed with two Swords, which thing was plainely ſignified by the two Hornes which he had, like the Lamb. But though the Beaſt would be the Lambs equall, and reſemble him in pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, yet his voice bewrayes him to be but a counterfeit, and a diſſembling hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrite: <hi>he ſpeakes like the Dragon,</hi> he pretendeth property to that which is not his own, and exalteth himſelfe againſt thoſe, unto whom he ſhould ſubmit and give honour: Even as the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon ſaid of the Kingdomes of the world;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.6.</note> 
                  <hi>All theſe are in my power, I give them to whom I will?</hi> So likewiſe ſaith this Beaſt his Vicar, the Prelate of <hi>Rome:</hi>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:97365:27"/>The Empire and Kingdoms of the earth are in my power, and at my diſpoſition, and to me it belongeth to depoſe and ſet up Emperours and Kings at my pleaſure, as ſhall be behovefull for the peace of the Church. And thus may the Beaſt in this be known by his voice, likewiſe in divers other particular blaſphemous ſpeeches and diveliſh doctrines.</p>
               <p>Further, it is ſaid of this Beaſt, <hi>That he exerciſeth all the power of the firſt Beast be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, and cauſeth the earth, and them which dwell therein, to worſhip the firſt Beaſt, whoſe deadly wound was healed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In that this beaſt is ſaid to exerciſe, <hi>All the power of the firſt Beaſt before him,</hi> therby was ſignified, That what the firſt beaſt could do by her motherly authority and power, under the uſurped title and name of the holy Church, the ſame could this beaſt do, by the authority and power of his father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, under the title &amp; pretence of Chriſts Vicar, &amp; <hi>Peters</hi> ſucceſſor, univerſal Biſhop, &amp;c. But that this Beaſt may yet further be diſcerned, it is ſaid of him, <hi>That he cauſed the earth, and thoſe which dwell therein, to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the firſt Beaſt, &amp;c.</hi> By cauſing the earth to worſhip the firſt Beaſt, was foreſhewed, that the Pope would exact
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:97365:28"/>of the earth the tenth part of the fruits thereof, for the maintenance of the holy Church, and this is indeed to worſhip: For as the paying of Tithes in the time of the Law, was a part of the true out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worſhip of God, ſo this is the worſhip of the Beaſt. And further, by cauſing the Inhabitants of the earth alſo to worſhip the firſt Beaſt, was ſhewed that he would carefully ſee due homage, ſervice, and obedience to be yeelded and performed to the holy Church: ſo that though the Prelate of <hi>Rome,</hi> as a ſon of Perdition, did exalt himſelfe above mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, yet ſtill doth he maintaine the power and dignity of the Catholike Church; the eſtimation of her Motherhood muſt ſtill be maintained, her voice muſt ſtill be heard and obeyed; not to come when ſhe calls, is contumacy and contempt, not to be indured; they that dare ſo far to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe her authority, as not to obey her Paritors Proceſſe, are by her doom to be accounted curſed children, and worthy of no leſſe cenſure and puniſhment, then to be ſtruck with that terrible Thunderbolt of her Excommunication, the violence whereof is ſuch, as who can indure it?
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:97365:28"/>Who will not rather ride, run, dance at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance, crouch, kneele, pay, pray, or do any thing elſe, which Maſter Officiall or his Regiſter will enjoyne them, then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo ſo heavie a burthen, as the cenſure of Excommunication? Thus will the Pope have the magnificence of this <hi>Diana</hi> to be maintained; The earth and thoſe which dwell in it muſt yeeld unto her the Tithe of all their increaſe, as alſo Mortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aries, Offerings, and many other Church duties, which ſhe requireth of them; for ſhe is a Goddeſſe, and muſt be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And this diminiſheth the Popes glory never a jot, the two eſtates of the Whore, and falſe Prophet, can well agree and ſtand together, as Father and Mother in one Family, and therefore the ſecond Beaſt, as Father of all, will have the firſt Beaſt worſhipped; that is, obeyed and maintained in glory, as Mother of all. And further obſerve, in that the Pope hath execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all authority of the Catholike Church, thereby is confirmed the truth of the expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, that the firſt Beaſt was the Catholike Church, and the ſecond Beaſt the Pope, as hath been before obſerved.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And he doth great wonders, ſo that he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:97365:29"/>fire to come down from Heaven on earth in the ſight of men.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, by the wonders which he did, was foreſhewed what wonderfull things the Prelate of <hi>Rome,</hi> that falſe Prophet ſhould bring to paſſe; as namely, under the title of the ſervant of the ſervants of God, (which indeed all Miniſters of the Word, and other Church Officers ought to be) to creep up and exalt himſelfe above Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours and Kings, and all other eſtates in the earth, which being conſidered, is indeed a thing wonderfull: for firſt, the Prelacy and Cleargie, in reſpect of the pretended holineſſe of their Orders, were exempted and freed from being ſubject to any ſecular juriſdiction and power,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſ, Can.</hi> 9.10.</note> the meaneſt of them might not bee produced before any ſecular Judge, for any crime or offence how hainous ſoever, yet unto this Beaſt, they muſt be obedient in all things, as ſervants to their Lord; upon him they muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend with all obſervation, as children up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their fathers: And as for Emperours and Kings, and other worldly States, it is plaine to be ſeen, that though they ſtand highly upon their titles and dignities, not
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:97365:29"/>to have them impaired, or in any thing di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſhed, which is a thing which they will withſtand, to the ſhedding of abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of blood; yet to be made ſuch vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals to this Beaſt, as to hold his ſtirrop, to lead his Horſe by the bridle, to kiſſe his feet, they thought it no abaſement, but an honour: And notwithſtanding, that very many of that beaſtly ranke have been no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious wicked men, and abominable li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, yet have they the craft ſo to delude and beſot all people, of all degrees in the world, as to bring them to believe that the truth is ſo infallibly annexed to that ſeat of the Beaſt, that it is not poſſible for him to erre in judgement; yea, he made the world to believe it as an Article of faith, that his determination and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of any controverſie, or point of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, is a more indifficient and infallible rule of faith then is the holy Scriptures: That theſe and the like groſſe doctrines is beleeved and received, are great wonders.</p>
               <p>Further, <hi>He maketh fire to come down from Heaven on the earth, in the ſight of men, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By fire in this place was foreſhewed the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:97365:30"/>puniſhment which ſhould be inflicted on the Saints, which was burning with fire: And in that the fire was ſaid to come from Heaven,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6</note> wherby was foreſhewed, that the Iudges of the earth, <hi>Who are called gods,</hi> and their ſeats as the Throne of God in Heaven, ſhould be ſo corrupted by the Pope, as that they ſhould believe the Saints and Servants pf God, which refuſed to obey the Pope and his Laws, to be therefore Heretikes, Schiſmatikes, refra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctary, rebellious and diſobedient perſons, and therefore ſhould condemne them to be burnt to death: This they have done, thinking they did God there in good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and that it was the juſt judgement of God upon them. Thus he made fire to come down from heauen: For true it is, that the judgements rightly pronounced by the lawfull Magiſtrates, are the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, and their puniſhments, Gods puniſhments, and therefore it is that Magiſtrates are called Gods: but ſeeing Magiſtrates have been thus corrupted by the Pope, and made to pronounce unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and unjuſt judgements, we are to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem them as the judgements of the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon; and yet nevertheleſſe their autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:97365:30"/>and power lawfull, and ordained of God. Thus the Beaſt deceiveth them that dwell on the earth, by means of thoſe Miracles (falfly ſo called) which he had power to do in the ſight of the Beaſt, as is ſhewed in the verſe following.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ,</hi> 14.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And he deceiveth them that dwell on the earth, by the meanes of thoſe Miracles which he had power to doe in the ſight of the Beaſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe which the Beaſt deceiveth, are ſaid to dwell on the earth; that is, have their affections ſet upon earthly things, and not upon heavenly, ſo that they will not for love of the truth forſake their earthly poſſeſſions and pleaſures: theſe are they which are deceived by theſe ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wonders of this Beaſt; but thoſe that are ſtrangers and Pilgrims in this world, whoſe affections are ſet upon heavenly things, and not upon earthly, theſe are not deceived, nor deluded by him: theſe making tryall of him by Gods Word, have found him to be a lyer and a deceiver, and believe him not, but taking their lives in their hands, witneſſe againſt him to the death; that his power and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king is of Satan, and that his wonders are lyes.</p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:97365:31"/>
               <p>And Whereas it is ſaid, that he had power to do <hi>theſe Miracles in the ſight of the Beast:</hi> thereby is confirmed and made manifeſt, that which before is ſhewed, to wit, that this ſon of Perdition, the chiefe Darling of his holy Catholike Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is preſent with her, and in her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and for her ſake, and in her behalfe exerciſeth his power, ſhe retaineth ſtill her former authority, without any dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing thereof, as is euident unto all that are acquainted with the acts of that Church. Thus much for the ſecond part of this Chapter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:97365:31"/>
               <head>THE THIRD PART OF the XIII. Chapter of the REVELATION.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Wherein is foreſhewed a third Beaſt, which was ſet up by the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this ſecond Beaſt the Pope, who ſaid to <hi>them that dwelt on the earth, that they ſhould make an Image to the Beaſt which had the wound with a ſword, and did live.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>HEre we may ſee that the Pope by his commaunding power was the cauſe of ſetting up this Image, and for the better and more cleare vnderſtanding. what this Image is, Let us a litle conſider the patter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, whoſe Image and liknes it beareth, namely the firſt Beaſt.</p>
               <p>The firſt Beaſt as hath beene ſhewed, was the repreſentative body of the Catholick Church Militant, conſiſting of the ſelect Prelacy and Preiſthood of ſundry Nations, gathered together into one counſell or Synode, with authoritie to make Lawes, and canons for the vniverſall Church, to be obſerved uniformely of all Nations under
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:97365:32"/>pretence of the inſufficiency of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for the goverment of the Church, and the worſhip of God, in like manner the Pope, (in his wiſdome ſeeing it neceſſary for the good goverment, maintenance, and upholding of his kingdome, and the roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out of Heretickes, and ſeditious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, (as they call them which daily increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in every countrie) did ordeyne and command,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilium La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundum, Can,</hi> 6.</note> that in every province there ſhould yerely be held and kept a provinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all counſell or Synode conſiſting of the Prelats and many other ſelected perſons which ſhould look to thoſe matters, to which Synode he alſo gave power to make Lawes atd ordinances, to which the people ſhould be conformable and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent: This is the Image which he cauſed the dwellers on the earth to make of the Beaſt, which had the wound with a ſword and did live.</p>
               <p>Further it is ſaid,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verſ.</hi> 15.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erſe.</hi> 15. <hi>And power was given him to give life unto the Image of this Beaſt, that the Image of the Beaſt ſhould both ſpeake, and cauſe that as many as would not worſhip the Image of the Beaſt, ſhould be killed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this Verſe we may obſerve: firſt, that
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:97365:32"/>a gift was given to the Pope to beſtow upon this Image: Secondly, what this gift was, <hi>viz.</hi> to give life or breath to the Image: thirdly, the end and effects of the gift, which was, that the Beaſt ſhould ſpeak, and cauſe that as many as would not worſhip the Beaſt ſhould be killed: As there was given by the Dragon to the firſt Beaſt, great power and authority, and alſo a mouth to ſpeak blaſphemies, and to make war with the Saints, in like manner by the ſame Dragon was this gift given to the Pope, to give life or breath to this Image: By life is here meant authority, which is, the life of a Synod, without which it is of no force, and ſo this Image ſhould have been no more then a very Image or pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, and ſet up to no purpoſe, but the Pope having received it, gave autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to the Image that he ſhould ſpeak, that is, make and ſet forth Canons and Laws; for to ſpeak is ſo underſtood: as for example: A King is ſaid to ſpeak to his ſubjects when he ſetteth forth his Laws and Proclamations: ſo this Beaſt having made Canons and Decrees, ſpeaketh to her vaſſals and ſubjects by them.</p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:97365:33"/>
               <p>Moreover, the Image cauſed, that as many as would not worſhip him, ſhould be killed: Here the pride and cruelty of this Image is ſet forth, to be anſwerable to the firſt Beaſt, and therefore rightly is he called her Image: for as the firſt Beaſt made war with the Saints, and overcame them, all that dwelled on the earth worſhiped him, &amp;c. ſo whoſoever would not worſhip this I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage; that is, heare his voice, and keep his commandements, there was no way for him but death. All the worſhip that the Lord requireth of his ſervants,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.12, 13.</note> is, <hi>That they feare him, walk in all his waies, love him, and ſerve him with all their hearts, &amp; with all their ſoules to keep the Commandements of the Lord, and his Ordinances,</hi> And this is indeed the true worſhip of God. In like maner, this Image will be worſhiped, his Laws muſt be obſerved, and his Canons obeyed without examining and trying of them, be they never ſo unholy and unjuſt: They that do not obſerve and obey them, be they never ſo upright and holy men, they ſhall be thereby indited, arraigned, judged, and condemned to death, as being in their eſtimation, Heretikes, Schiſmatikes, diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient and rebellious perſons, contemners
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:97365:33"/>of God, and of the Church, yea, as the filth and of-ſcowring of the world, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of the ſociety of men.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And he cauſeth all both ſmall and great, rich and poore, free and bond, to receive a Marke in their right hand, and in their foreheads.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Image challenging worſhip to be performed unto him, of all people of all ſorts and degrees, according to the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity given him by the Pope, was by ſome contradicted and deſpiſed, wherefore the Image in policy, for the better triall of thoſe that were his truſty ſubjects and ſlaves, ordained that all his Miniſters ſhould receive a Marke, at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving whereof, they ſhould vow and ſweare to be of his Dominion, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Banner, to fight againſt Chriſt and his Saints, What this Marke is, and what is the maner of giving and receiving of it, is now to be declared.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>For proofe of this, look no further then in the</hi> 36 <hi>Canon of the Church of England,</hi> An. 1603</note>
               </p>
               <p>The Prelacy and Clergie being as hath been before ſhewed, aſſembled with au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to make laws, did ordain that every Biſhop in his Dioceſſe ſhould carefully obſerve that none ſhould preach or execut the functio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a pariſh Parſon, Vicar or Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, in any Pariſh, but he that would ſwear
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:97365:34"/>to obſerve their Lawes and Canons, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon ſhould receaue the letters of orders of the Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, which let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of orders ſigned and ſealed by the Biſhop, is the Marke of the Beaſt here mentioned, and doth teſtifie in the behalfe of the bearer thereof that he is their ſworne ſervant, under holy orders, either a Prieſt, a Deacon, or a half prieſt, &amp;c. and that he is a man found capable &amp; meete for the cure and charge of ſoules, and therefore to what pariſh ſoever theſe tried lads are ſent to doe ſervice, upon ſight of this marke, they muſt be receaued without ony opoſition, upon penaltie of the law upon thoſe that ſhall refuſe them.</p>
               <p>Here may be obiected, that this marke is only receaued by the Clergie, and not by the people of all ſorts, rich and poore, bond and free, according to the text. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that all perſons which receaue the falſe Preiſts doe likewiſe receiue, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to that authoritie which ſent them, and alſo the marke by which they are ſent, as is-evident, when a Prieſt cometh to take poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of a pariſh to which he is apointed by the Biſhop; he is not receaued upon his word, nor becauſe he tolleth the bell, and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:97365:34"/>and putteh on the Surplice, and uſeth other Cerimonies enioyned him by the Prelate: But ſhewing the foreſaid Marke of the Beaſt, they receaue both him and it, and communicate with him: thus all both ſmal and great, rich and poore, bond and free, that ſubmit unto their apointed Preiſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue a marke in their foreheads, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaving and ſubmitting to him. For as our ſauiour Chriſt faith of his Apoſtles and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtors, <hi>He that receaueth you, receaueth mee, and he that Heareth you heareth me.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 16. <hi>Iohn</hi> 20.</note> So thoſe that receaue, heare, and ioyne in fellowſhip with theſe falſe Miniſters, doe heare, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, and joyne to the falſe power which ſent them, and the marke by which they are ſent:</p>
               <p>whereas it is ſaid that they receaved the marke in their foreheads, <hi>or right hand,</hi> thereby was ſhewed that this marke ſhould be an aparent teſtimony that they were ſervants of the beaſt, and that they were of that band which had ioyned hands, &amp; made a league to walke in the wayes of deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
               <p>Further, it is ſaid; <hi>Verſ.</hi> 17. <hi>And that no man might buy or ſell, ſave he that had the marke of the Beast, or the na<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e of the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:97365:35"/>Beaſt, or the number of his name,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here is propounded three conditions, and whoſoever had not one of them, thereby to be known to be of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, might not buy or ſell, or have any thing to do amongſt them. For the better underſtanding hereof, let us minde, that although theſe three Beaſts in reſpect of their ſeverall power and juriſdiction did differ one from another, the Catholike Church being the chief, and the Pope in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to her, and the Image of the Beaſt as it were a ſervant or handmaid, inferiour to them both, yet notwithſtanding they were one body, being joyned and knit to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by the power of the Dragon, and have ſo farre prevailed over the Nations, as that they have brought all, both ſmall and great, rich and poore, bond and free, to bee in ſubjection to their Kingdome, which beareth the name of the holy Catholike Church, or Sea of ROME,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 14.8 <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1.</note> but the Holy Ghoſt cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it BABILON THE GREAT CITIE: for as the materiall <hi>Babylon</hi> was a City which <hi>dwelled upon many waters,</hi> which cauſed her to abound in riches and treaſure: ſo this myſticall Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:97365:35"/>this great Citie of <hi>Rome,</hi> I meane the Eccleſiaſticall State, is ſaid alſo to ſit upon many waters, which the Holy Ghoſt expoundeth to the People and Nations, as in the ſeventeenth Chapter, and 15, verſe: <hi>The Waters on which the Whore ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, are Peoples and Multitudes, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Tongues:</hi> And theſe Waters have been the means of the flowing and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing of the wealth and riches of this Citie, ſo that their Merchants, that is, the Prelates have grown rich, and become the great men of the earth, by trafficking in them; alſo the Ship-maſters (which are the Pariſh Prieſts) and all Ship-men and mariners (which are the inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our guides, and Eccleſiaſticall Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers) have gathered crums, and wax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed rich thereby, and therefore at the deſtruction of this great Citie ſhall ſtand <hi>a farre off and ſhall howle to ſee the deſolation thereof,</hi> and their owne gaine taken away, for from thence-forth no <hi>man will buy their commodities any more.</hi> Here note, that theſe foreſaid ſpirituall perſons are the ſellers, and the Lay-people are the buyers, and the wares which are bought &amp; ſold in this kingdom <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:97365:36"/>called ſpirituall, as pardons for ſin, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences of divers ſorts, which is a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall commodity, and bringeth in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of treaſure, alſo their Piſtling, Goſpelling, Chanting, Homeling, Maſſing, which muſt be maintained with the Tithes, or Tenth of all things, which they uſually call the maintenance of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery; Alſo the Sacrifices (unacceptable to God, and well-pleaſing to the Divell) which are daily offered at their Altars, and at divers Images of Saints; alſo the body of their Maker and Saviour: beſides Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying, Baptizing of Children, Churching of Women; Houſeling the ſick, burying the dead; theſe and many ſuch like, are the ſpirituall Wares ſold in this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, which have particular prizes ſet on them: Now ſo it is, that theſe wares are priviledged, that none may either buy or ſell them, ſave he that hath the <hi>Marke of the Beaſt, or the name of the Beaſt, or the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his name.</hi> What the Marke of the Beaſt is, hath been before ſhewed: Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the name of the Beaſt is to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, For the manifeſtation whereof let us conſider and minde, that thoſe which did preach and profeſſe Chriſt and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:97365:36"/>his doctrine, are ſaid to have and to <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eare his Name. The Lord Chriſt Ieſus ſaid unto <hi>Ananias</hi> in a Viſion concerning <hi>Paul, That he was a choſen Veſſell to beare his Name before the Gentiles, and Kings,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 9.15.</note> 
                  <hi>and the Children of Iſrael.</hi> By the Name of the Lord, here was meant that <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould preach the doctrine of Chriſt, and thoſe that beleeved by his Preaching, were ſaid to believe in the Name of Chriſt, and were therefore baptized into his Name, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Chriſtians.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 11.26.</note> 
                  <hi>The Diſciples were first called Christians in Antioch.</hi> Alſo the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and followers of Chriſt are ſaid to have <hi>the Lambs Fathers Name written in their foreheads:</hi> According to this is the meaning of the name of the Beaſt, which the holy Ghoſt ſetteth down in a myſterie in the 17 Chapter, and 5 verſe, <hi>Babylon the Great, the Mother of Harlots, the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the earth:</hi> But the Papiſts call it not <hi>Babylon the Great,</hi> but the great uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall or Catholike Church; not <hi>the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Harlots,</hi> but the Mother of all true Beleevers; not the Mother of <hi>all abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the earth,</hi> but the Pillar and ground of Truth, that cannot erre: This is the difference betwixt the name which
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:97365:37"/>God giveth them, and which they take and attribute unto themſelves: But let them ſpeak the beſt of themſelves, and let us conſider and anſwer them in their own language, they call themſelves the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, and their profeſſed vaſſals and ſubjects are therefore called Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, and whatſoever they be, that do ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preach or profeſſe the Catholike faith, that is, beleeve as this Catholike Church beleeveth, that it is Mother of all true Beleevers, that it cannot erre, &amp;c. they are Catholikes, ſuch perſons whereſoever they live, if they thus believe (although they never received the marke of the Beaſt, nor can receive it) yet this profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is enough to intitle them in the right of buying or ſelling theſe foreſaid wares, ſuch perſons have the name of the Beaſt, and therefore they may buy pardons of the forgiveneſſe of part, or all their ſins, and uſe any of theſe things which they ſuppoſe neceſſary for their ſouls health: (but indeed deſtruction) yea, after their death they may, for a ſumme of money given to the foreſaid Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants by their charitable Succeſſours, be releaſed out of Purgatory: thus, by
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:97365:37"/>their own diſcription we have found out the name of the Beaſt, and who they are that have received it.</p>
               <p>The third condition is the number of his name, as the Beaſt had one generall name which is the Catholike Church) whereby he was known from all other States and Kingdoms in the world, ſo it hath a number of names belonging to the particular parts and members thereof, to diſtingniſh one from another, as in the 17. Chapter, and third verſe, <hi>The Beaſt was full of names of blaſphemy.</hi> As the true Church, which is that body whereof Chriſt Ieſus onely is the Head, is compleat and furniſhed, when it is coupled and knit together by every joynt and member, which Chriſt Ieſus hath given for the furniture thereof; namely, <hi>Apoſtles, Prophets, Evangelists, Paſtours and Teachers:</hi> So this falſe Church being fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed with thoſe parts and members which that great red Dragon hath inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſet up, under the title of Miniſters of Chriſt, to work upon the children of diſobedience; namely, the <hi>Pope, Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches, Cardinals, Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Deanes, Arch-deacons, Abots, Priors, Prebends
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:97365:38"/>Canons, Chancellers, Commiſſioners, Regiſters, Doctours,</hi> with the reſt of the ſelected Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod or Counſell: ſo (I ſay) this Church or Beaſt, being furniſhed with theſe mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, are the full number of his name; that is, they are the number of whom the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church conſiſteth, and from them all inferiour power and offices of Miniſtry, as Monks, Friers, Parſons, Vicars, Curats: and Jeſuits are derived. This I underſtand to be the number of his name, and this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition agreeth with that in the verſe following, where it is ſaid, let him that hath underſtanding count the number of the Beaſt, what can be underſtood but the Number of the particular parts whereof he conſiſteth? And where it is ſaid, <hi>For it is the number of a man.</hi> What can be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood but that it beareth the reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance and likeneſſe of a man? as follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to be declared. Thus we ſee who may buy and ſell in this Kingdom, and who may not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Here is wiſdom; let him that hath under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing count the number of the Beaſt, for it is the number of a man, and his number is</hi> 666.</p>
               <p>Here is ſhewed, firſt, what is required
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:97365:38"/>in ſearching out this myſtery, and that is wiſdom and underſtanding, not ſuch as is from beneath, but from above, which commeth down from the Father of lights, from whom commeth every good and perfect gift, he it is that giveth wiſdome to the ſimple, and the underſtanding of his ſecrets to thoſe that feare him; which ſhould teach thoſe that deſire to know the Myſteries of his will, to labour to be ſuch as to whom he hath promiſed to reveale them, then whatſoever we aske, we ſhall receive of him, for to ſuch he giveth libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and upbraideth not.</p>
               <p>Secondly, here is ſhewed a direction how to imploy a mans wiſdom in finding out this Myſterie, and that is, by counting or reckoning the number of this Beaſt.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, a reaſon why the number of the Beaſt is to be counted, <hi>Becauſe it is the number of a man;</hi> that is, it agreeth with, and is anſwerable to the parts of a man, and ſo is the more eaſily to be found: for as we know the true Church of Chriſt is compared in the Scriptures to the naturall body of a man, as in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. <hi>For as the body is one, and hath many members, and all the members of that one body being many
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:97365:39"/>are one body, ſo alſo is Chriſt Jeſus:</hi> And in the 27. verſe, the Apoſtle ſpeaking of the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> he ſaith: <hi>Yee are the body of Chriſt, and members in particular, &amp;c.</hi> So in the <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.22, 23. <hi>Chriſt is given to be Head over all things, to the Church which is his Body.</hi> Thus as the true Church is called and compared to a body; ſo the Catholikes affirme, that they onely are that Church, and that Body, and that the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular parts and members of their Church are the full number thereof. Now whereas they ſay they are the Church, let us ſay they are the Beaſt. And whereas they ſay, their particular parts and members make up the number of the Church, let us ſay their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular parts &amp; members make up the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Beaſt, and ſo we finde the true interpretation of this Scripture.</p>
               <p>Further, here is ſet down the number of the Beaſt, which is 666. By this num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber I do not underſtand any ſet number, and that the parts and members of the Beaſt are no more nor leſſe, but thereby I underſtand is meant a full and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat number, as before was ſhewed: As all the parts and members of a man joyned together make a whole per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:97365:39"/>man, ſo do the particular parts and members of the Beaſt make a perfect and entire Beaſt. Thus briefly, according to the ability which God hath given me, I have gone over this Chapter, wherein is briefly ſet forth the workers of iniquity, which have done, and yet ſtill do pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile over Gods people, under the title of Miniſters of the Goſpell, and Church of Chriſt, as they were repreſented un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the forme of three ſeverall Beaſts: The firſt Beaſt repreſenting the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Counſels, or (as the Papiſts call it) the Catholike Church. The ſecond Beaſt repreſenting the POPE. And the third Beaſt, the PROVINCIAL COUNCELS, which were eſtabliſhed by the Pope.</p>
               <p>The which three Beaſts bearing rule and Dominion in theſe times whereinto we are fallen, and being enemies and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers of Chriſt and his Kingdom, it doth behoove us to know them, to the end that wee may eſchew them and their evill wayes, and ſeek after the truth, making ſtrait ſteps unto the Kingdom of God.</p>
               <p>Now, that we our ſelves may make parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:97365:40"/>uſe hereof, it is neceſſary for us to examine the Nationall Synod, or Convo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, conſiſting of the Prelacy and Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of the Land, who whilſt they remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned under the yoke and bondage of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and whilſt they exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed their power, which was firſt given them by the Pope, for, and in the behalfe of that Church and Dominion, they were the very Image of the firſt Beaſt before mentioned: But being now ſeparated from the Pope, and Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> they think (as it ſhould ſeem) that their ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Pontificall power and authority which they exerciſe is lawfull and warrantable, and to be ſubmitted unto: They being gathered together, boaſt themſelves to be the repreſentative body of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the true Church of Chriſt, and that they have power to make Laws and Canons for Government thereof, and for the worſhip of God, which all men ought to yeeld obedience unto, as appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth by divers of their Bookes of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons.</p>
               <p>But we are not to take this upon their word, but to make triall thereof by the Word of God, whether it be true or falſe.
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:97365:40"/>If the Word of God did give them ſuch power and authority, then indeed we were bound in conſcience to yeeld already obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their Lawes and Canons: But the moſt wiſe God, and Diſpoſer of all things, who knoweth the vanity of mens mindes, would not have his people to hold their faith in reſpect of mens perſons, and at their pleaſure to alter and change the ſame, and therefore did not give to any of his Miniſters power to make Laws in matters of Religion, and for the worſhip of God, but gave them power onely to teach the Nations to obſerve the things which he had commanded them, as in the 28. of <hi>Mathew,</hi> the 19. and 20. verſes. And the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> biddeth the Corin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1. <hi>to be followers of him, as he followed Chriſt,</hi> And in the ſame Chapter he alſo ſaith, <hi>That which he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived of the Lord, he delivered unto them.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Acts</hi> 15.</note> Alſo the Aſſembly of the apoſtles and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Church of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> they would not impoſe any yoke of bondage upon the Churches of Chriſt, but held it to be a tempting of God ſo to do, as before hath been ſhewed: And this agreeth with that in <hi>Deut.</hi> 12.32. <hi>Whatſoever I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:97365:41"/>you, take heed you do it; Thou ſhalt put nothing thereto, nor take ought therefrom:</hi> By which Scriptures it is plain, that the chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Miniſters of the Goſpell had no ſuch power as theſe Prelates preſume to have, as we ſhall finde, by examining their par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Canons and Conſtitutions, of which for examples, I will onely note ſome few of their late and beſt reformed Book, made <hi>Anno,</hi> 1603. in the firſt year of the Kings Majeſties reign, by which it will be apparant, that they paſſe the bounds of the Subjects of Chriſt, and that they have no power from him to make ſuch Laws; but by ſo doing, they uſurp the place of God to reign in mens conſciences, for unto him onely it doth belong to make Laws in matters of Religion, and for the worſhip of God, to which, men are onely bound to yeeld obedience, without adding, or detracting, and that for this their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, they are liable to the curſe of God, being indeed the Image of the Beaſt here ſpoken of, that is originally ſprung from the Dragon, and hath received power of Law-making from him. Concerning the firſt and ſecond Canons, wherein they pretend their zeal for the aboliſhing of all
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:97365:41"/>forraign power repugnant to the juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Kings Majeſtie over the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall eſtate, he being the higheſt power under God, to whom all men owe moſt loyall obedience; and that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie hath the like authority in Cauſes Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, as the godly Kings had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Iews. To theſe I do moſt willingly aſſent and agree: And further do deſire, that (as the Pope) ſo the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy, with all their Antichriſtian Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents which uſurp ſpirituall power and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periority, above the Majeſtie of Chriſt Ieſus, being a ſtrange and forraigne gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, brought in and eſtabliſhed in this Land by the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> may alſo be aboliſhed and caſt out after him: for by them the Pope lives in hope hereafter to be ſerved, as he hath been heretofore, to the great vexation of the Kings and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this Land, yea to the loſſe of their Crown and lives.</p>
               <p>But to be ſhort, I will proceed to men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſome few of their Canons, whereby iniquity is eſtabliſhed for a Law, and their beaſtlineſſe diſcovered. In the third Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non it is enacted, that whoſoever ſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme the Church of <hi>England,</hi> by Law eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:97365:42"/>not to be a true and Apoſtolicall Church, teaching and maintaining the doctrine of the Apoſtles, that perſon ſhall bee excommunicated, <hi>ipſo facto.</hi> That there are ſome, yea many doctrines of the Apoſtles maintained in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I do not deny; ſo there are in the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> But that the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall ſtate, or ſpirituall body poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike, which is called the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> which conſiſteth of Arch-biſhops, Dioceſan Lord-biſhops, Suffragans, Deanes, Arch-deacons, Prebends, Canons, Chancellours, Commiſſaries, with the reſt of the Clergie, as heads and guides of that body to go before, and the whole multitude of the Layitie (as they call it) which is as the Tayle to follow thoſe Heads, that this politicall Body is the Spouſe and Church of Chriſt, as they affirme in their ſeventh, eighth, and ninth Canons, that I do deny: For firſt, if it were true, that they are the Miniſters of Chriſt, which is his Church, we ſhould finde warrant for them in his Teſtament, wherein is ſet down the Miniſters which he hath ſet in the Church: namely, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, Prophets, Evangeliſts, Paſtors,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:97365:42"/>and Teachers; and alſo their office and adminiſtration: But in all the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, no Arch-biſhops nor Lord-bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, no Deanes nor Arch-deacons, Prebends, Prieſts nor Canons, no Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellours, nor Commiſſaries, and other their Court-officers, nor any ſuch admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration, as they challenge and execute, can there be found, they are a ſtrange ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration that is riſen up out of the earth, for earthly-minded and vaine men have invented them, and therefore the body which conſiſteth of them cannot of right bee acknowledged to bee the Body of Chriſt, whoſe Miniſters in reſpect that they are called according to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of Chriſt, are from Heaven: But it is indeed the Image of the firſt Beaſt, whoſe mouth was as the mouth of a Lyon, his body like a Leopard, and his feet as the feet of a Beare, an ugly compounded and deformed mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. And as their names are ſtrange, and different from the Miniſters of Chriſt, ſo is their practiſe contrary: they are not ſervants to the Flock and Church of Chriſt, and helpers of their joy, but they are authours of their woe, challendg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:97365:43"/>and exerciſing Lordſhip and Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on over their faith; for in ſtead of a due adminiſtration of the Word of God, they have mingled a cup of fornication for the people to drink, that is, deviſed a forme of Book-worſhip, with Orders, Rites and Ceremonies, which they have impoſed on the people, under the title of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service, and which they muſt obſerve without adding thereto, or taking any thing from it, as in the 4, 6, 7, 8, and 14. Canons.</p>
               <p>Further, they are not painefull Preachers, but lazy Lords; they are not followers of Chriſt and of his Word, but are contemners thereof, caſting it behinde their backs, and will not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, nor ruled by it, they are Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers much like <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> for as he would deſtroy all that would not worſhip his golden Image; So who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever doth refuſe to yeeld obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to their Lawes, ſhall bee moſt ſeverely puniſhed, as is plaine by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers penalties annexed to their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons.</p>
               <p>In conſecrating and ordaining Prieſts, they are like to <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> for as he conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:97365:43"/>whom he would of the baſeſt of the people, to be the Prieſts of the high places which he had ſet up, ſo do they ordaine for the moſt part ignorant fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows to be their Pariſh Prieſts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour Miniſters: wherein though they do moſt abſurdly, yet will they not bee contradicted, as we may ſee by the 57 Canon, where it is ſaid, <hi>whoſoever ſhall refuſe to communicate with a dumb and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preaching Miniſter, Let him be excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated.</hi> And although their owne Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours complaine and cry out againſt it, yet they will not amend: amongſt the reſt it is worthy to be obſerved what their own great Champion profound Maſter <hi>Hooper</hi> faith, <hi>viz. That both Arguments from light of nature, Laws and Statutes of Scripture, the Canons that are taken out of ancient Synods, the decrees and conſtitutions of ſincerest times, the ſentences of all antiquity, and in a word, every mans conſent and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, is againſt ignorance, in them that have the cure and charge of ſoules.</hi> If it be ſo how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable and beaſtly is it for the Prelates to ordain, allow, and approve of ſuch for the Miniſters of Chriſt, of which there are many hundreds in the Land, whom
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:97365:44"/>the Prelates are not aſhamed to forbid to expound the Scriptures, as in the 49 Canon, where it is ſaid, that ſome of their Pariſh Prieſts <hi>ſhall not take upon them to expound in their cure, or elſe-where, any Scripture, or matter, or doctrine, but ſhall onely ſtudy to read, &amp;c.</hi> It is greatly to be wondred at, that ſo many grave heads as were gathered together, and ſate conſulting about theſe matters, ſhould breed and bring forth ſuch abſurd and impious Canons. If there were nothing elſe, this allowance of dumb Miniſters, is ſufficient to ſhew the vanity of their mindes, and the darkneſſe of their fooliſh hearts: So that wee may truely ſay of them, that when they profeſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be moſt wiſe, by exalting, and making themſelves equall with God, in making Laws for the government of his Houſe, the Church, even then they became moſt fooliſh, and voide of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>As for the beſt ſort of their Pariſh Prieſts, which are men of learning, and gifts; they muſt alſo be confined within their limits, they muſt worſhip God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rules preſcribed them, by
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:97365:44"/>theſe their ſpirituall Fathers, as in the 38 Canon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If any Miniſter ſhall omit to uſe the forme of prayer, or any of the Orders or Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies preſcribed in the Communion Book, let him be ſuſpended, and if he do not conforme within the ſpace of a moneth, let him be depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</hi> The abſurdities and blaſphemies contained in that Comon Prayer-book, are many; which having been diſcovered and laid open by divers Treatiſes already publiſhed in print, I will omit, onely this I will adde, that in the impoſing of that Service Booke, or any other, this great iniquity is committed by the impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers thereof; That they do exalt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves both againſt Chriſt, who is aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into Heaven, and hath given gifts to his Miniſters,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.1, 11, 12.</note> for the gathering together of the Saints, <hi>for the worke of the miniſtery, and for the edification of the Church, his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy;</hi> and alſo they exalt themſelves againſt the Holy Ghoſt, who onely hath power <hi>to help our infirmities,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom,</hi> 8.26.</note> and to furniſh men with gifts, to worſhip God aright. Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, their Preachers may not teach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their corrupt Church ſtate and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, though they know it to bee Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:97365:45"/>nor againſt the forme of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip preſcribed in the ſaid Common-pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Book, nor againſt the ceremonies, nor the Government of the Church of <hi>England</hi> by Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, Deanes, Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons, and the reſt that beare office in the ſame, nor againſt the manner and form of making and conſecrating Biſhops, Prieſts, or Deacons, nor againſt the Laws and Ordinances <hi>Eccleſiaſticall,</hi> eſtabliſhed in the ſaid Church, whoſoever tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth in theſe things, ſhall be excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> as is plaine in the 4, 6, 7, 8, and 54. Canons. Thus by excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and curſing, they labour to maintaine and defend their corruptions, but not one jott of Scripture dare they ſhew, and no marvaile; ſeeing the whole Scriptures are againſt mens inventions and traditions, of which nature theſe abuſes are, being left here by the Pope, and retained and renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his Prelates. As they may not teach againſt theſe things, ſo on the contrary, they may not teach the true and right way which Chriſt hath preſcribed in his Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, how we muſt worſhip God, nor how the true Church of Chriſt ought to be gathered and conſtituted, the Miniſters
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:97365:45"/>thereof ordained, nor the manner how it ought to be governed, as appeareth in the 9.10, 11. and 12. Canons. By which we may ſee in what bondage their Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers are kept, they muſt hide their Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent in the earth, and put their candle under a Buſhed, leſt men by the light thereof ſhould come to the knowledge of the truth and believe it. Alſo it is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved as a generall rule, that none, good or bad, learned or unlearned, can be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to receive their Orders of Prieſthood or Deaconſhip, or be admitted to preach, or execute a Miniſtery in their Pariſh Churches, unleſſe they ſweare to conforme to the worſhip and ceremonies preſcribed by theſe Prelates, and alſo ſubmit to their Anti-chriſtian rule and govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which they challenge to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, as being Lords over all: Thus by ſwearing they make their inferiour Prieſts to ſell themſelves to worke wickedneſſe, which trick they have cunningly deviſed to bring the Land in ſubjection to theſe Antichriſtian yoke: And upon the taking of this Oath, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Prelates Marke, which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in this Chapter, <hi>the Marke of the Beaſt:</hi>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:97365:46"/>which is underſtood to be the Letters of Orders under the Prelates hand and Seale, to teſtifie that they are made Prieſts or Deacons, according to the Order and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons preſcribed in that behalfe, in this their Convocation, as we may ſee in the 36, 48, and 50 Canons: And for refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to worſhip them in theſe things, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are put back, and thoſe that formerly have been ordained, for refuſing ſo to do, (which they call revolting) have had their penall Laws executed upon them; which is Suſpenſion, Degradation, and Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, and after theſe many other afflictions in body, goods and name; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accounted factious and ſeditious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, that have no right to buy or ſell their Wares.</p>
               <p>Concerning the people, whereof the Church of <hi>England</hi> conſiſteth, it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary that we finde them ſuch as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures do require, otherwiſe they can<gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> be accounted the Church of Chriſt, and to this end obſerve theſe few places fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing: <hi>Ezeck.</hi> 44.19. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, no stranger uncircumciſed in heart, and uncircumciſed in fleſh, ſhall enter into any San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary:</hi> And the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> for ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:97365:46"/>ſuch uncircumciſed ſtrangers to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into the Sanctuary of the Lord, hee calleth them <hi>a rebellious people, that had po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted his Sanctuary, and broken his Covenant;</hi> And in the 23 verſe, The Lord teacheth his Miniſters to put difference betweene the holy and prophane, the cleane and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane; And according to this was the practiſe of the Apoſtles in the Primitive Age, who by preaching the Word, gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red none but ſuch as beleeved, and volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily ſubmitted themſelves to walke ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the profeſſion of the Goſpell; and if any did cunningly creep into the fellowſhip of the Saints, and not walke accordingly, they were to be caſt out by the Church, as in the 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. Likewiſe the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> he ſeparated the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Epheſus</hi> from thoſe that beleeved not; ſo the Apoſtle taught the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.14, 15, <hi>&amp;c. Be not unequally yoked together with unbeleevers, for what fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip hath righteouſneſſe with unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, And what communion hath light with darkneſſe? And what concord hath Chriſt with Belial? Or what part hath he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeveth with an Infidell? And what agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hath ehe Temple of God with Idols?
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:97365:47"/>For ye are the Temple of the Living God, as God hath ſaid, I will dwell in them, and walke in them, and I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people; Wherefore come out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and be ye ſeparate, faith the Lord, and touch not the uncleane thing, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now if we compare the Church of <hi>England</hi> with theſe Scriptures, we ſhall finde that the practiſe and proceedings thereof, hath been, and is contrary. The people thereof (for the moſt part) are ſuch as viſibly and apparantly live in all kinde of licentiouſneſſe, and in their workes deny God, being abominable and diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedient. For theſe Lordly Prelates be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing armed with the Sword of Civill au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and having the Law of their ſide, they have not laboured by painefull preaching to draw men to the obedience of the faith, and to the fellowſhip of the Goſpell apart from the prophane and wicked, that ſpeak evill of the waies of the Lord, but they have compelled and inforced all ſorts of people, both religious and prophane, not onely ſuch as feare God, but alſo ſuch as feare him not, by bodily puniſhments to be conformable
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:97365:47"/>to the profeſſion which is by their Canon Law, eſtabliſhed in this Church: As if the Word of God, that Sword of the Spirit were not mighty enough in opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the gathering together of the Saints. That this is their practiſe is plain by the 90. and 114. Canons, where it is ſaid, that Miniſters and Church-wardens muſt preſent all perſons above the age of thriteen years, that come not to the Church and receive the Sacraments, after which preſentation, if they doe not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, they ſhall bee excommunicated, impriſoned, and have their goods atta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched: This is the means which hath been uſed for the gathering of this Church of <hi>England,</hi> whereby they have confounded and mingled them together, whom God hath commanded to be ſeparated: wherein what do they leſſe then think themſelves wiſer and ſtronger then God? The Word of God is the ſeed whereby the Church of God is begotten, and thoſe that are begotten by any other means are baſtards, and not Sonnes: for as that Woman is an Harlot which hath Children by any but her law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Husband: ſo that Church whoſe
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:97365:48"/>members are gathered by any other way or means, then by the Word of Go<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwading and moving their hearts, the ſame is not the Church of Chriſt: But this hath been the manner of gathering the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and therefore it is unworthy to be adorned with the title of the Church, but ought to be accounted the Image of the firſt Beaſt before ſpoken of, that is, of <hi>Great Babylon, which is an habitation of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels, an hold of foule Spirits, and a Cage of every unclean and hatefull Bird.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And for confirmation hereof, by the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of their own mouthes, let us but conſider the eſtimation which the mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of this Church have one of another: Some there are amongſt them, who for making more conſcience of their waies then the reſt, are in diriſion called <hi>Puritans</hi> or <hi>Preciſians;</hi> theſe on the contrary ſeeing the ungodly converſation of the reſt of their brethren, eſteeme them as wicked, prophane, carnall, and unregenerate men, ſuch as (for the moſt part) are mockers, contemners, and evill ſpeakers of the truth, and in whom is no appearance of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the feare of God; and therefore they diſtinguiſh the better ſort from theſe
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:97365:48"/>prophane perſons, by the name of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours.</hi> This is the eſtimation which they have one of another, which is a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt note that they are not come into the order of the Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>I deny not but there are many amongſt them, that are the Saints and Servants of Chriſt, that are godly and zealous people, which ſo far as they know, they labour to yeeld obedience to the Commandements of Chriſt; and although by meanes of their Guides which make them to erre and go aſtray, keeping them in ignorance of this doctrine, yet it ſhall go well with them: Such perſons (I ſay) as fitt ſtones for the building of the Church of Chriſt, but ſo long as they remaine in this confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, they can no more be ſaid to be the true viſible Church of Chriſt, then a heap of ſtones fitted for a building can be ſaid to be a Houſe, therefore they muſt be ſeparated from the wicked, and placed together, according to the order preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed by Chriſt Jeſus, and practiſed by his Apoſtles, as in the New Teſtament, before they can be ſo eſteemed.</p>
               <p>As theſe Prelates will have this Church of <hi>England</hi> to be accounted the true
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:97365:49"/>Church of Chriſt, ſo they will have the true Church of Chriſt to be accounted falſe, ſchiſmaticall, and hereticall, as in the 9. 10. and 11. Canons: by which it doth appear, that if any people ſeparate from this corrupt Church ſtate, and joyne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther apart from the wicked and prophane, to walke in all the waies and ordinances of Chriſt preſcribed in his Teſtament, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging Chriſt Ieſus to be the onely King, Lord, and Law-giver, in matters of Religion, and the worſhip of God, which is the true and right rule whereby Gods people ought to walke, and by ſo doing, they become indeed, the true Church of Chriſt, to whom he hath promiſed his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and bleſſing: yet notwithſtanding, ſuch perſons, are for this to be accounted Schiſmatikes, and to be excommunicated, <hi>ipſo facto,</hi> as holding wicked errours. Thus they open their mouthes wide, to ſpeake evill of the waies of God, whereby alſo they appeare to be the very Images of the Beaſt, that blaſphemed the Tabernacle of God, as is ſhewed before, upon the ſixth verſe.</p>
               <p>Further, whereas the Apoſtles did or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine divers Elders in every Church, to
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:97365:49"/>whom they gave charge to feed the Flock of Chriſt, whereof the Holy Ghoſt had made them Overſeers: On the contrary, theſe Prelates, in ſtead of Elders to feed one Flock, they do ordaine one idle prieſt to be fed of divers Flocks; that is, ſome to have two, ſome three, and ſome foure Benefices; and this they are not aſhamed to publiſh, as appeareth in the 41 Canon, by which it is allowed, that Licences and Diſpenſation ſhall be granted to Maſters of Arts, and other Graduates, to have plu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of Benefices, ſo that they be within the compaſſe of 30. miles.</p>
               <p>Concerning their Copes, Surplices, Croſſing in Baptiſme, and other their foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Ceremonies, which they themſelves acknowledge to be things indifferent, yet thoſe that refuſe to uſe them, through the tenderneſſe of their conſciences, are there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore greatly afflicted and perſecuted, ſo far are they unlike the Apoſtle (who would not uſe neceſſary things, that were offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive to his brethren) as that they themſelves will, not onely uſe thoſe things which are unneceſſary, but alſo in their uſe, juſtly ſcandalous and offenſive; yea, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell their brethren alſo to uſe them, which
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:97365:50"/>if they refuſe, they ſhall enjoy neither li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, nor worldly poſſeſſions. How un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy this their practiſe is, for thoſe that would be accounted Chriſtians, let the world judge: certainly, it is ſo, contrary to Chriſtian charity, as that it is to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted Heatheniſh impiety, and beaſtly cruelty, and it is a Marke in their foreheads to teſtifie unto the world that they are thoſe which our Saviour Chriſt ſpeaketh of, that ſhould <hi>come in Sheeps clothing,</hi> (that is, pretending themſelves to be the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Goſpell, and ſuch as deſire peace and unity) <hi>but inwardly are ravening Wolves:</hi> ſuch as do ſow ſtrife and conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and by this meanes they grow rich, filling themſelves with the ſpoile of their Brethren, whom they perſecute, as Lions, Beares and Leopards, fill themſelves with their prey.</p>
               <p>Theſe, and many other evils by their Canon Law eſtabliſhed, and to the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God, and vexation of his people daily practiſed, have been much oppoſed, and the iniquity of them ſufficiently ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted, but as yet it remaineth like unto the Decrees of the Medes and Perſians, that may not be changed: yea, they boaſt
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:97365:50"/>and ſay (like their old Mother) that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their Laws, the Church of Chriſt would run into confuſion, as if the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Laws of Chriſt were not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient for the government of his Church and Kingdom. Thus they open their mouthes, and reproach the Almighty: <hi>But he who ſitteth in the Heavens laugheth them to ſcorne, and will vexe them in his ſore diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> if they repent not.</p>
               <p>By theſe few examples of their wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed practiſes, I have briefly ſhewed, that this Church of <hi>England</hi> ſtill remaineth under the bondage of Antichriſt, and is ruled and governed by the Image of the Beaſt, mentioned in this 13 Chapter, which uſurpeth that power, which is onely proper to Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
               <p>And whereas it is objected in the behalf of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that it is fallen and ſeparated from <hi>Babylon,</hi> the univerſal Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and therefore it is the true Church of Chriſt, and needs no other ſeparation.</p>
               <p>To this I anſwer, that true it is, that that great City is now divided into three parts, as was foreſhewed in the 16 Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this propheſie, and the Cities of the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:97365:51"/>Nations (that is, the Nationall Churches, whereof the Church of <hi>England</hi> is one,) are fallen from it; but this is no argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that therefore they are the true Churches of Chriſt, that are divided from <hi>Rome,</hi> unleſſe they be united and joyned to Chriſt, and framed and built together, according to the patterne preſcribed in his Teſtament.</p>
               <p>It is indeed an argument, that this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom ſhall not long ſtand, as our Saviour Chriſt teacheth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 12. <hi>Every kingdom divided againſt it ſelfe, is brought to deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: and every City or Houſe divided againſt it ſelfe, ſhall not stand. And if Satan caſt out Satan, he is divided againſt himſelf: how ſhall then his kingdom stand?</hi> Thus by the diviſion of this Great City, Gods people may receive comfort, and rejoyce in aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red hope, that the fall and deſtruction of <hi>Babylon</hi> is neare, and that the Lord will ſhortly be avenged of their iniquities, which ſhould teach us, to <hi>come out from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, that we partake not of their ſins, and ſo receive of their plagues, and to have no fellowſhip with their unfruitfull workes of darkneſſe, but rather reprove them, and sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fastly reſiſt and fight againſt them. So ſhall
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:97365:51"/>we receive the Crown of righteouſneſſe, which God the righteous Iudge ſhall give at his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing. To whom be glory and Dominion for ever and ever, Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>REVEL. 20.4.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>And I ſaw the ſoules of them that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed for the witneſſe of Ieſus, and for the Word of God, and which had not worſhiped the Beaſt, neither his Image, neither had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived his Marke upon their foreheads, or in their hands, and they lived and reigned with Chriſt a thouſand years.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
